<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the conference holden before the French King at Fontain-bleau between the L. Bishop of Eureux, and Munsieur de Plessis L. of Mornay, the 4. of May 1600. Concerning certaine pretended corruptions of authors, cyted by the sayd Munsieur de Plessis in his booke against the Masse. Faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109408</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845056</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19948)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 494:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the conference holden before the French King at Fontain-bleau between the L. Bishop of Eureux, and Munsieur de Plessis L. of Mornay, the 4. of May 1600. Concerning certaine pretended corruptions of authors, cyted by the sayd Munsieur de Plessis in his booke against the Masse. Faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[dward] A[llde] for Matthew Selman and William Ferbrand, and are to be solde [by Mathew Selman] in Fleete-streete, next the Inner Temple gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Recounts the proceedings at the conference to examine Mornay's "Traité de l'institution de l'Eucharistie".</note>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Du Perron, Jacques Davy, 1556-1618.</term>
               <term>Mornay, Philippe de, --  seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623. --  Traité de l'institution de l'Eucharistie --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mass --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9932:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9932:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE OF THE CONFE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENCE <hi>HOLDEN</hi> before the French King at <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-bleau, betweene the L. Biſhop of</hi> Eureux, <hi>and</hi> Munſieur du Pleſsis <hi>L. of</hi> Mornay, the 4. of May 1600. Concerning certaine pretended corruptions of Authors, cyted by the ſayd <hi>Munſieur du Pleſsis</hi> in his booke againſt the Maſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by E. A. for Mathew Selman and William Ferbrand, and are to be ſolde in Fleete-ſtreete, next the Inner Temple gate. 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9932:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9932:2"/>
            <head>A true diſcourſe of the conference held at <hi>Fontaine-Bleau</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>May. 1600.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince that the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reux</hi> perſwadeth himſelf, that the diſhonor and ouerthrowe of the Doctrine Preached in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, of the Realmes of <hi>Fraunce, Almaine, England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and, Denmarke, Swethen</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and, &amp;c.</hi> Dependeth on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the Lord <hi>Pleſsis</hi> booke, written vpon the Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> (which doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is maintained by this book, as it may be gathered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his priuate letters to the L. <hi>Pleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is.</hi>) As if the Miniſters of all the Kingdomes in this laſt endeuour, had put all their heads into one body, to be cut off by this new <hi>Hercules</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from hel. And ſith for hauing onely deflowred cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine places of the ſaid book, he boaſteth of the victory, &amp; cauſeth <hi>Te Deum</hi> to be ſung in euery place: Let no man blame vs if by this our writing, wee oppoſe the truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe falſhoods which haue beene publiſhed, ſince we are thereunto bound by the duety which we owe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and for the inſtruction of his people.</p>
            <p>Truth it is, that ſince L. <hi>Pleſſis</hi> booke of the inſtitution of the Sacrament was publiſhed, ſome haue found out no other meanes to trauerſe the courſe thereof, then by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9932:3"/>both in word and writing, that the places by him alleadged, as wel of holy Scripture as the Fathers, were falcified; yeelding ſufficient teſtimony by this their ſiniſter ſubtilty, that his allegations auerred &amp; iuſtified, the doctrine he profeſſed ſhould be both cleare, certaine and inpugnable.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe he patiently endured this ſlaunder, partly endeuouring himſelfe to ouer-throw it by his anſweres, partly truſting that of it ſelfe at laſt it would giue place to verity: Vntill he had intelligence that the bruite thereof had come to the Kings eares, yea and got ſo great creadit as he verily beleeued it. Wherupon agreeued (yea &amp; that iuſtly) he deſired that hee might come to his iuſtification. And for that there were ſome that laboured to diuert cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Gentlemen of the religion vnder this pretext; he tooke occaſion to requeſt the L. Biſhop of <hi>Eureux</hi> by a priuate letter, that both of them might ioyne together in a moſt humble petition to his Maieſty, that it might pleaſe him to appoint Commiſſaries, before whome the booke might be therby examined, to whom in eſpecially he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed himſelfe, becauſe the ſaid Biſhop was the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall author of the ſaid euill report, &amp; wrote ordinarily to his friends in diſgrace of the ſaid L. of <hi>Pleſsis;</hi> &amp; by certain his ſuffragans publiſhed the ſame from houſe to houſe, &amp; as it were from doore to doore. By this meanes the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> promiſed himſelfe, that the ſaid L. Biſhop vpon this priuate letter ſent vnto him, by the handes of his brother, would without any further trouble, repayre to <hi>Paris;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by accord of both parties, his Maieſty might ordaine ſuch a one of his Priuy counſell as he thought moſt fitte to deliuer him a true report of their conference. In which caſe the matter being manadged with this ſilence and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, his Maieſty might haue no other intereſt then the knowledge of the truth: (A care worthy of ſo a great
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9932:3"/>King and the tytle which he beares) to know aſwell the good as the euill fayth of a ſeruitour, accuſed of falſhood before him: a cryme alwayes haynous, but more hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous in reſpect of the ſubiect, being matter of Conſcience and Diuinity.</p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe the ſaid Lord Biſhop tooke a quite oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite courſe, ratling out vppon this priuate and modeſt let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a publique and inſolent booke which he cauſed to be Imprinted in his owne houſe, and publiſhed at <hi>Paris:</hi> by which, of this perticuler controuerſie, he made a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique quarrell, and of two perſons, two factions; calling all the Catholique Romaine Church to warrant: interreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the King in all that he might in this cauſe, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to diſwade the examining of the booke propoſed by the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis,</hi> whoſe iuſtification he knew too well that he could not ouer-throw. For which cauſe hee articled falſely againſt the ſaid booke, to draw vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the tytle and quallity of a Plaintife, and vndertooke to approoue in preſence of his Maieſty, fiue hundred heynous and groſe errours, manifeſt and without <hi>Hiper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole:</hi> yea ſuch ſayth he as they may be iudged by the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looking on, vpon the opening of the booke, without entring into the iudgement of the ſence. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he offered himſelfe further, beſides that to make it appeare, that there was not in that book one onely place but was eyther falſely, impertinently, or vnprofitably al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged. Theſe were the very wordes (which the reader may note) vpon what ground hee generally taxed the whole booke.</p>
            <p>To this booke notwithſtanding the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the King, and according to his owne nature, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with great modeſty, reuealing the matter as much as in him lay from a publique to a perticuler triall twixt the Biſhop and himſelfe, from partyes by him pretended,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9932:4"/>to their ſeuerall perſons. So that by ſome, this ſame ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of his anſwere was ſcarce wel interpreted. But for that he knew that the ſayd L. Biſhop had ſent a Coppy of that which he had publiſhed, and written with aduantage en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough vpon the ſame ſubiect to his Maieſty, he was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailed likewiſe to write vnto him, beſeeching him moſt humbly to vouchſafe to enter into the approbation of his ſayd book, by the grant of certayne Commiſſaries of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient knowledge, that might haue the charge to examine the ſame, from the one ende to the other: in publiſhing whereof he proteſted that he aymed at no other end, but to prepare his ſubiects heartes, and make them capable of the ſeede of ſo holy a reformation in his time.</p>
            <p>The Doctors of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> likewiſe were ſodainely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed againſt this propoſition, apprehending a ſerious examination of this booke, and perceiuing well in theyr conſciences, that it could not take effecte, but to their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and indignity: They appointed certaine Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates amongſt them to make relation hereof to the popes <hi>Nuncio:</hi> who fore-ſeeing too wel to what inconuenience it might tend, ſought out the King, to certifie him hereof; Beſeeching his Maieſty that it might paſſe no further: and laying before his eyes the iſſue therof: Annexing alwaies to all that he had vrged, moſt inſtant complaints againſt the Author and the booke. But hereupon there were ſome that aſſured him, that the matter ſhould be carried with ſuch Art, &amp; with ſuch aduantage for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Pope could not but content himſelfe therewith, and namely in theſe wordes: that the diſgrace ſhould light vpon the Heretiques, and hence-forward the <hi>Nuncio</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſatiſſied, who before had been in great perplexty, which is to that ende reckoned vp, that the ſequell of the hiſtory may be better be comprehended.</p>
            <p>Some few dayes after the Biſhop of <hi>Eureux</hi> came to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9932:4"/>the Court, where hee was entertained of his Maieſty with an extraordinary applauſe; euery houre whiſpering in his eare, ſuggeſting him with all thoſe ſubtilties, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> either hee could inuent or deuiſe, to bring his enterprize to a good end. On the other ſide the Lord of <hi>Pleſſis,</hi> in what place ſoeuer hee preſented himſelfe, eyther his Maieſtie ſpake not vnto him, or if he did, it was ſo coldely, that he might manifeſtly perceiue, that hee tooke ſmall pleaſure to talke with him; yet notwithſtanding the meanes of this pretended conference, was concluded vpon twixt him and his oppoſite, and the King thought it good to appoint the conference to bee held at <hi>Fontaine-Bleau,</hi> during the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourniment of his Parlament.</p>
            <p>The Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> arriued at <hi>Fontaine-Bleau</hi> the 27. of Aprill, and the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> the 28. at noone, vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, or vncalled: yet notwithſtanding the L. of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reux</hi> would already demaund an Acte of his compatitiue againſt him, for defaulting in his appearance but one day; and yet the Commiſſaries aboue named, were ſent, the day appointed for conference; and all this without eyther giuing him in word or deed notice thereof, yea at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting himſelfe before the King, he neuer ſpake vnto him of it, nor any one in the behalſe of his Maieſty.</p>
            <p>Theſe proceedings together with the precedent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo extraordinary, made him bethinke himſelfe; ſo that hee humbly beſought the King to graunt him audience; which hee did the laſt Sunday in Aprill, after ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes.</p>
            <p>His purpoſes were, that nothing had more pierced his heart, then when he was giuen to vnderſtand, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty did beleeue that hee had vſed corruption, eſpecially in a thing ſo Sacred. That this his iuſt griefe made him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the meanes whereby his Maieſty might conceiue the truth, which was very eaſie for him to doe, if ſo be he had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9932:5"/>no other intention to know the ſame: that if the affayres had been contynued in theyr firſt termes, he ſhould not be in any ſort greeued; for that if they had beene managed with ſilence and diſcreation, his Maieſty ſhould haue had no other intereſt, but to haue iudged betweene his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghtnes and the others ſlaunders. But ſince that in truth, by the cunning of the Biſhop of <hi>Eureux</hi> it had been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhed through the whole Realme, and preuayled ſo farre as both the Pope and his <hi>Nuncio</hi> were pryuy thereto, hee ſaw well that his Maieſty ſhould be made beleeue that it highly concerned him, to ſort this action to ſuch an ende whatſoeuer it coſt him, that the Pope might be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Romaine Church aduantaged: Conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that hee had this ill hap to haue his iudge intereſſed in this cauſe, to haue his King and his Maſter for a party op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite. That if the queſtion were but of his life and honor; he would coſt them at his feete, and Sacrifice them to his ſeruice: But in that he was bound to the defence of truth, wherin Gods honor was in queſtion, he humbly beſought hys Maieſty to pardon him, if he ſought iuſt and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes to warrant and defend himſelfe: and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of his Maieſty had ſufficiently informed him, by the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres which he made him from time to time, that he was truely tryed by the nature of his affayres, to oppoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt him. The motiues which the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to his Maieſty at that time, were theſe.</p>
            <p>The 1. correſpondent to the firſt propoſition by him propounded to the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> that it might pleaſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty to giue charge to the Commiſſaries to examine &amp; in order to verifie, al the places of his book, aſwel for the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the truth, as the manifeſtation of his faith &amp; honor, &amp; the rather becauſe the L. Biſh. had generally condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his whole booke. This offer his Maieſty was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled to reiect, in that hee was certified by thoſe that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9932:5"/>this affayre, that it appertained to the L. of <hi>Eu.</hi> who accuſed him to impugne ſuch places as him liſt, wheras if the matter had bin handled vprightly, the publike intereſt was to know the truth of the book, &amp; to proceed likewiſe in termes of iuſtice, that it ought not to be iudged as a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, by ſome clauſe; but rather to bee examined as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, by the depoſition of wytneſſes, that is to ſay of the <hi>Places</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fathers; amongſt which if there were ſome one leſſe anſwerable, it myght not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> al that weake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſolide proofe &amp; perfection of the reſt. But the truth was, that the perpetual luſtre of the truth in the aprobatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the places, had made cauil &amp; reproach for ſhame to hide their heads.</p>
            <p>The 2. was, that becauſe ſome one prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that the firſt was too long, that the Commiſſ. ſhould examine onely the places of the booke which ſhould be impugned as falſe by the L. Biſh &amp; that thoſe w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> he excepted not againſt, ſhuld be held for iuſtifiable as touching the letter; the intire au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority remaining in the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> to examine the ſence.</p>
            <p>A neceſſary meanes if it were ſought, to attaine vnto the knowledge of the truth, ſince that it was the queſtion as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to examine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of the L. of <hi>Pleſsis,</hi> in the allegations of his book: yet alwaies without preiudice of the doctrine of the Romaine church, ſince that the L. of <hi>Eureux</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in a readines to diſpute vpon the ſence. Yet was this reiected no leſſe then the former, and for the ſame cauſe; becauſe the places not impugnable, wold haue bin ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as they wold haue ouerſhadowed the reſt; &amp; ſo ſtrong &amp; eminent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in preſence of their light, ſome places ſought out here &amp; there, eyther indifferent, or of ſmal importance could not haue appeared.</p>
            <p>The 3. that if theſe two were refuſed, it might pleaſe his Maieſty to appoint the L. Biſh. to deliuer to the L. of <hi>Ples.</hi> ſuch exceptions as he had againſt his book, but at leaſt the 500. hainous, euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; litteral vntruths by him prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, &amp;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9932:6"/>without ouer-vrging them, to the end that the ſaid L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> might prepare himſelfe to giue ſatisfaction: the which he offered to performe in ten daies, and to the end that no time might be loſt, to begin from the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and continue euery day after, in explaining (in his Maieſties preſence) ſo many of his errours as the houres &amp; times would affoord him leaſure.</p>
            <p>A matter practiſed ordinarily in all iuſtice, grounded vpon the offers made vnto him, and the expreſſe written words of the L. of <hi>Eureux,</hi> by reaſon he ſaith that he hath coated them already: yet contrariwiſe calumnious, if hee had ſo ſaid, yea that aſſuredly in that hee hath them not. And yet notwithſtanding all this reiected, vnder ſome fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous aſpectes alleadged by the ſaid L. of <hi>Eureux,</hi> which ſome held for ſound reaſons; that for hauing named 5. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, he was not bound to particulate them. That he kept his word if he nominated but ten, or leſſe; and further that it were too much trouble for him to write them, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>But truely by a former reſolution betweene thoſe that managed this affayre, it was concluded, to giue the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> whatſoeuer aduantage he might deſire: and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the ſayd Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> of whatſoeuer Iuſtice he could require; ſo that he might ſcratch either by right or wrong, ſome number of places choſen out of fiue thouſand and more, to inferre an appearaunce of preiudice againſt the whole booke.</p>
            <p>Thus this three meanes were in all humility propoſed vnto the King, by the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis,</hi> not onely by word of mouth, but by a moſt humble petition alſo, the which his Maieſty commaunded him to giue to the Lord Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor. But after he had preferred the equitye of his cauſe to his Maieſty by all theſe reaſons, which to him ſeemed moſt requiſite, his aunſwere was that he would ſend for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9932:6"/>the ſaid Lord Chancellor, and giue him commiſſion to bring the Lords of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> and <hi>Eureux</hi> to agree vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the forme: And preſently his Maieſtie ſent for them.</p>
            <p>The ſame day toward euening, the L. Chancellor ſent for the L. of <hi>Pleſsis,</hi> and began to diſcourſe vnto him, that the King had tolde him that he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him the charge to warne the ſayd L. of <hi>Pleſſis</hi> to be ready for the ſayd conſerence: and therefore that it muſt needs be that eyther his Maieſty had forgotten to commaund him, or himſelfe, to ſpeake to the ſayd Lord of <hi>Pleſsis.</hi> Whereunto the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> aunſwered, that it ſufficed, in caſe he would remember (as hee did) that hee had not ſpoken vnto him.</p>
            <p>Thus after ſome ſpeaches, he deliuered him the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he had preſented to his Maieſty; and becauſe there was ſome difference about the forme, he deſired him to vouchſafe to conſider vpon the three aforeſayd offers. But the two formoſt were abſolutelye reiected vnder pretence that the chalenger of falſehood might ſet vpon his party where he liſt: without reſpect that the queſtion concerned the quotation of a booke, which (to ſpeake vprightly) helde of the nature, not of a contract, but of an inqueſt: the diſputation was wholy ſettled vpon the laſt. The ſayd L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> pretending that ſith this matter was ſpoken of as to be handled in tearmes of Law, he being the Defendant, was not to be denyed his Aduerſaries action of falſehood, that he might an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere thereunto. ſith that vnder pretence of forme of lawe, he had bene denyed the examination of the whole booke, thereby to miniſter opportunitye to the L. of <hi>Eureux</hi> to impugne him in what place he liſt. And that in this matter he looked for Iuſtice at the ſaid L. Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celors hands, which he aſſured himſelfe he very wel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in this his petition: otherwiſe, that beſides that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9932:7"/>he ſhould haue cauſe to proteſt againſt the ſayd Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> vpon ſlaunder, hee ſhould vppon refuſall of ſo lawfull conditions haue no leſſe argument to doubt of too manifeſt partiallity.</p>
            <p>The end was this, that the ſayd Lord Chauncellor ſent for the ſayd L. of <hi>Eureux,</hi> with whom he ſpent ſome 3. quarters of an houre; then comming into his Gallery, where the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> wayted his anſwere, he tolde him that the ſayd L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> would not heare of the deliuery of his action of falſehood, much leſſe of his fiue hundred places. That he did not thinke himſelfe bound therto by his writing; that the writing of them wold aske a month and a halfe, or more: that in tearmes of law to require a condition impoſſible, and not to yeeld to doe any thing, was all one, and matter alike.</p>
            <p>The L. of <hi>Ples.</hi> replyed, that in his opinion hee craued but right before all Iudges whatſoeuer; that the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> in ſhrinking from his propoſition, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the whole booke, had bound himſelfe to his owne offer, that in truth hee beleeued that hee could not poſſibly performe the fiue hundred vntruthes by him promiſed: well might he peraduenture deliuer in fiue hundred pretended, ſith he had them ready tolde; ſith alſo that hauing anſwered his book, he had no more to doe but to draw them out: Otherwiſe, how could he purge himſelfe of ſlaunder? Finally the L. <hi>Pleſsis</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding that he might not depart from this laſt courſe, and that the ſaid L. Chauncellor (the next morning) would make report thereof to the King.</p>
            <p>Munday the firſt of May the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> heard of nothing, but that the L. of <hi>Eureux</hi> ſtill ſtood vpon his denyall to deliuer his fiue hundred places, and ſtill was at the Kinges elbow to make him comprehend that this was not the way to come to his pretended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9932:7"/>and the ſame day there arriued the Preſident of <hi>Thou,</hi> M. <hi>Pithou,</hi> M. <hi>Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubon,</hi> and the Phiſition. <hi>Martin</hi> whom his Maieſty had moſt earneſtly ſent for; The laſt man of theſe being brought in by the L. of <hi>Eureux,</hi> could not conceale his paſſion in this matter, but bare himſelfe as a party. To them did his Maieſty declare, that he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them not to be Iudges, but only interpreters, in caſe there ſhould grow any controuerſie about the ſpeeches, but reſerued to himſelfe the iudgement. And heere is to be noted, that only <hi>Caſaubon</hi> was of the religion: wherof notwithſtanding the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> made no inſtance.</p>
            <p>Tewſday the ſecond of May, about eyght of the clocke at night, the L. Chauncellor ſent for the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> to intimate vnto him the Kinges pleaſure. The ſumme was this, that the King had ordained that the <hi>L.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Eureux</hi> ſhould in his Maieſties preſence open the booke, &amp; ſhew vnto him one after another, thoſe places wherein he pretended falſehood, to the number of 50. if time would ſo permit: whereto he muſt preſently aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere in order as they ſhould be propounded: for ſayd he, it was to be ſuppoſed that the ſayd Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> hauing produced them, ſhould at all tymes bee ready to anſwere. (Heere let the reader iudge what memory could bee capable of ſo many reaſons, preſently to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere ſo many obiections; for muſt hee not by that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count be alwayes prouided for all, albeit he were aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but with ſome?) Moreouer that if hee could not fit himſelf to this condition, his Maieſty was reſolued in his owne preſence to haue the falſehoods by the <hi>L.</hi> of <hi>Eur.</hi> pretended, to be verified in his abſence, to the end to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine therof according as reaſon required: as alſo by his ſtanding vpon his words, he gaue him to vnderſtand that he concealed more rigour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he yet ſhewed; ſtil vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſundry times y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had that night to reſolue himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9932:8"/>
            <p> Neyther did the ſaid L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> fayle to lay open vnto him the extreamity of this condition, which could not be ſo preciſely impoſed vpon him, but with a manifeſt reſolution to oppreſſe the truth in his perſon. That if hee did not plainely perceiue a match made, hee could well enough brooke any condition: but that he muſt needes be blinde, if hee could not perceiue the ſame throughout the whole progreſſe of this matter. Likewiſe that that was the onely cauſe that hee ſtood ſo ſtedfaſt vpon his demaund. As for the examining of his booke behinde his backe, ſo as it might bee duely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in his abſence, the more ſhould bee his honour: if vnduely, the leſſe reproach; as alſo ſuch as ſhould haue charge, ſhould beare the greater burden, as well in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as conſcience.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, that all the world might ſee that hee proceeded beyond all reaſon, onely vpon a deſire that his Maieſty might bee the more plainely enformed of his ſincerity and iuſtice, hee deliuered a fourth propoſition, which in writing hee deliuered to the L. Chauncelor, to this effect; That he would bee content that the L of <hi>Eureux</hi> ſhould conſigne into the handes of the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, of <hi>Thou</hi> &amp; <hi>Calignos,</hi> eyther of the Preſident <hi>Thou</hi> only (becauſe <hi>Calignos</hi> was ſicke) his 5. hundred preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vntruthes, to the ende that dayly hee might in hys Maieſties preſence anſwere vnto fifty of them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order of the booke, that ſo much the more eaſily he might prepare himſelfe for thoſe that follow: with condition likewiſe that vpon the breaking off of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, the ſame might be returned into the hands of the Lord <hi>Pleſsis.</hi> The which propoſition the ſayd L. Chauncelor receiued, to report thereof to his Maieſty, &amp; thereof to giue him anſwere.</p>
            <p>This matter thus reported to the King vpon Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9932:8"/>morning the 3. of May, and conſunation holden with the Lord of <hi>Eureux,</hi> they procured the King to bee incenſed vpon this; that the ſayd Lord of <hi>Pleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that the fiue hundred pretended vntruths ſhould be committed into the hands of my L. the Preſident of <hi>Thou;</hi> That it might content him to haue them commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into his Maieſties hands, who had truſted him with greater matters; that his enemies had taken no ſurer gadge then his owne word: much rather therefore ſhould a Seruaunt, yea euen a houſholde ſeruant: thus ouerthrowing the ſubſtaunce of his reaſons with theyr great words.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the L. of <hi>Pleſſis</hi> being ſent for into the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery at <hi>Fontaine-bleau,</hi> receiued this ſecond decree at the mouth of the L. Chauncellor; That he ſhould in the Kings preſence aunſwere to the places propounded by the Lord of <hi>Eureux,</hi> vpon the opening of his bookes, as is aforeſayd: otherwiſe that if he would not accept of this condition, his Maieſty would cauſe the booke to be ouer-looked and examined in his abſence, &amp; thereof to determine as he ſhould thinke good.</p>
            <p>And indeed ſo ſoone as the L. of <hi>Pleſſis</hi> had declared that (in regard of his reaſons ſo often propounded) he could not depart from his laſt propoſition, all the Court was warned to aſſemble in the great Hall, at three of the clocke in the after noone, to be preſent at this examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; (but it was againe put off vntill the next morning at eyght of the clocke) neyther was there all that day any other ſpeech in Court, but that they would vppon contumacy, proceede with all rygour againſt both the Author and the booke.</p>
            <p>Many circumſtances myght heere be added, as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of the ſtomackes of thoſe men, that had in this matter vndertaken to ſatiſfie the Pope: who alſo made
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9932:9"/>ſhew of great commodity to his Maieſty. But it may ſuffice that the ſame were noted, euen by the moſt paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, who by the proceedinges, haue in their mindes weakened the pretended ſucceſſe, throughout the whole courſe therof.</p>
            <p>Laſtly about ten of the clocke at night, the Lords of <hi>Caſtelnau</hi> &amp; of <hi>Chambaret</hi> came to viſite the L. of <hi>Pleſsis;</hi> and in the Kings name, propounded vnto him that the L. of <hi>Eureux</hi> was reſolued to quote vnto him 60. places in his booke, whereunto hee ſhould in his Maieſties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence aunſwere in the morning at eyght of the clocke. The time was ſhort, the houre vnfit, and the match ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly made: Yet notwithſtanding (ſuch was Gods will) the Lord of <hi>Pleſſis</hi> ſhut his eyes agaynſt all theſe foreſeene inconueniences, and contrary to hys for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reſolutions, accepted of the condition; and to the ende that heereafter the force of the truth may appeare, as no doubt it will, in that there was nothing omitted that might darken the ſame; and yet in it ſelfe it will finde brightneſſe enough to pierce through all darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>About one of the clocke after midnight the Lord of <hi>Caſtelnau</hi> brought the 60. places: this was but a waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of hys tyme. About two of the clocke he had the bookes of the Lord <hi>Eureux</hi> brought him: (For ye muſt note that hee had none there) the places were quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſimply, <hi>Carolus Magnus</hi> p. 816. <hi>Scotus</hi> p. 869. <hi>Durandus</hi> p. 870. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without note of falſehood, and without any explanation. The Lord of <hi>Pleſſis</hi> neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe together with the difficulty of his ſight, doth in haſt peruſe them to the number of nineteene. About ſixe of the clocke in the morning the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demaundeth his bookes: at eyght of the clocke hee is commaunded to appeare.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:9932:9"/>
            <p> Now againe growes another difficulty; the Lord of <hi>Ples.</hi> telleth the King that hee had no leaſure to peruſe any more then nineteene, euen ſuch as came firſt to hand, as he light vpon the bookes: his Maieſty doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth whether the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> will proceede; he hath reaſon to the contrary, becauſe the Lord of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> hath choſen to his aduantage. Heerto the Lo. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that he had the bookes but 4. houres, and that in the night; That out of fiue thouſand places the Lord of <hi>Eur.</hi> had choſen threeſcore ſuch as liked him, and that it was very likely that he had produced y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ſufficient: ſo that he beſought his Maieſty to pardon him, albeit he were forced to ſay that this was more then extraordinary ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour: Heerupon held they a conſultation with the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> for the ſpace of one houre, who in the end accepted of the nineteene places: alſo to affoord him the more leaſure, the conference was deferred vntil after dinner.</p>
            <p>This was vpon Thurſday the 4. of May in the Bath Hall, in preſence of the King, with the aſſiſtaunce of the whole Court. To beginne, his Maieſty declared that he had no meaning that they ſhould diſpute of the Doctrine, onely he would they ſhould examine the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations of the places. Then did the Lord Chauncellor proceede, who briefly did expound his Maieſties mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Next the Lord of <hi>Eureux,</hi> who for his argument vndertooke to commend him, in that he would not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude into matter appertayning to the Church. And conſequently the Lord of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> who briefely dyd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that in as much as it was his Maieſties pleaſure, he was there ready to aunſwere for his booke; that he neuer writ it vpon any ambitious intent, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dyuerted him therefro, in regard of the preſeruing of his Maieſties moſt gratious fauour: And alſo the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9932:10"/>zeale for to preuayle during his Raygne, for a holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the Church, for the which many good men had long grieued. If to that purpoſe it might doe any ſeruice, hee ſhould thinke himſelfe moſt happy, with whatſoeuer loſſe: otherwiſe, that himſelfe could be the firſt man to wiſh it burnt, yea euen with his own hand.</p>
            <p>Howbeit that he did hope that vpon vpright exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, all the world ſhould finde that hee had vſed all ſincerity and great diligence: albeit it was not greatly to be maruailed, that among 5000. places or more, there might paſſe ſome few, wherein his eye, his memory, or euen his iudgement might waner: which yet were ſuch as could be of no importaunce, to hurt the truth that he therein handled. For (ſavd he) were all the bookes of the Doctors of the Romiſh Church, that haue bin writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten within theſe hundred yeares, as rigorouſly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned! where ſhould wee finde one that could abide the proofe? Beſides (with his Maieſties leaue) he proteſted, that this was a perticuler action, &amp; conſequently could not preiudice the Doctrine of the reformed Churches of the Realme, which was before him, and ſhould be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, and ſo continue for euer. And then did they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the matter.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt place out of <hi>Scotus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt place that the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> did ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">The 4. book of the Euchariſt. c. 9 p. 869. l. 26. of the firſt edi. P. 936. lyne 2. of the 2. edition P. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. l. 25. of the 3 edition.</note> was taken out of the 869 Page, lyne 26. of the Lord <hi>Pleſsis</hi> booke of the inſtitution of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> namely within eyght leaues of the ende (heere let the reader iudge what methode this is to examme a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9932:10"/>book) according to the firſt edition in <hi>quarto,</hi> which heer we will follow, (ſauing that we will alſo in the margent quote the pages of the ſecond or third editio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) where we read theſe words. <hi>Iohn Duns, called Scot, neere a hundred yeares after the counſel of Latran durſt bring into queſtion whether Chriſtes body be really contained vnder the formes; &amp; diſputeth that he is not.</hi> Againſt w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> place he pretendeth two matters: the one that <hi>Scot</hi> maketh it not a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, whether the body of Chriſt bee really contained vnder the formes, except in like manner as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Schooleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe to diſpute of matters moſt reſolued; as <hi>Whether there be a God? Whether there be but one god, &amp;c.</hi> The other, that the L of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> had taken the oppoſition for the reſolution; &amp; in both theſe matters he pretended hainous vntruths. To the 1. the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> aſwered, that wheras he ſaid that <hi>Scot</hi> had brought into queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Whether the body of chriſt be really contained vnder the formes,</hi> he vnderſtood it <hi>by the way of tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and his meaning did ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently appeare, firſt in that in the Chap, which is the ninth of the fourth booke, he entreateth <hi>of the abſurdities &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions proceeding of the tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Secondly, becauſe in the ſame it is ſayd, <hi>A hundred yeares after the Councell of Latran,</hi> that is to ſay; after the Article of tranſubſtantiation was eſtabliſhed. To the ſecond; that albeit the Schoolemen doe diſpute their queſtions, <hi>in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramque partem,</hi> yet doe they withall ſhew their owne inclination, yea ſometimes their perticuler reſolution, ſauing that they make it to ſtoop to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And this did the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> vpholde to appeare in <hi>Scot</hi> in the de duction of this matter, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where he handleth the ſecond member of this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Qualiter illud eſt poſsibile quod creditur; How the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty that is beleeued is poſſible.</hi> For after many diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, growing to the reſolution, he vſeth theſe wordes,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9932:11"/>which were ſhewed to the Lord of <hi>Eureux;</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Scorus printed at Paris, by Io. Granion, Spon the <hi>4</hi> of the Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. diſt. <hi>10.</hi> queſt. <hi>1</hi> pa. <hi>63.</hi> b. lit. E.</note> 
                  <hi>Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this article, it ſeemeth vnneceſſary to haue recourſe to the conuerſion of the bread into the body of Chriſt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering that euen from the beginning, that this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Sacrament was beleeued, it was continually beleeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the body of Chriſt altereth not out of his place in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to be heere, and yet was it not thus manifeſtly beleeued at the beginning of this conuerſion, as it ſhall bee ſayd diſt. xi.</hi> And let the reader note that ouer agaynſt this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle that beginneth,<note place="margin">Quantum ad iſtum artien'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, nonvidetur ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giendum eſſe ad conuerſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in corpus Chriſti, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio exquo res imius ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fuit credita, fuit ſempercre ditum, quod corpus Chriſti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n mutatur de loco ſuo in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elo vt ſit hic, &amp; tamen non fuit in principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o ita manifeſte creditu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de iſta conuerſione vt dicetar diſt. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Quantum;</hi> it is quoted in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, <hi>Reſolutio-Scoti, Scots reſoluſion.</hi> So that by <hi>Scots</hi> reſolution the Church did not alwayes beleeue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertion; the conuerſion is not neceſſary in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Therefore did not the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> in this place take <hi>Scots</hi> oppoſition inſteed of his reſolution. And this was gathered very briefe by ſuch as writ for either ſide, namely the Lords of <hi>Grigny, Paſquier</hi> and <hi>Vaſſaut,</hi> as likewiſe was all the reſt that enſued. Howbeit in that which the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> conſequently dyd alleage concerning the xi. Diſt. of the 4. booke q. 3. <hi>Scots</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion did yet more clearely appeare: For after he hath cited <hi>Jnnocent</hi> the 3. <hi>de offic. Miſſae, par.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. to prooue three opinions vpon this argument. The firſt,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ctus in</hi> 4. <hi>ſentent. D.</hi> 11. <hi>qu.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 31. <hi>lit. B.</hi> Circa hoc erant tres opiniones, Vna, quod panis manet, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſo vere eſt corpus Chriſti: Alia, quod panis non manet, &amp; tamen non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, ſed decinit eſſe, vel per annichilatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel per reſolutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in materiam, vel per cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in aliud: Tertia, quod panis tranſubſtantiatur in corpus, &amp; vinum in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumem.</note> 
                  <hi>That the bread remayneth, and yet the body of Chriſt is with the bread.</hi> The ſecond, <hi>That the bread remaineth not, and yet is not conuerted, but ceaſeth to be, whether by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made nothing, whether by being reſolued into the firſt matter, or corrupted into any other thing.</hi> The third, <hi>That the bread is tranſubſtantiated into the body, the wyne
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9932:11"/>into the bloud;</hi> He conſequently commeth to ground the firſt opinion verye ſubſtantially; in that hee ſayth,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> iſta Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiatione.</note> 
                  <hi>That the truth of the Euchariſt may be kept without tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Secondly,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et pancis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ctis.</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia pants cum ſuis acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a que poteſt eſſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut ſola accidentia; imò magis, quia ſubſtantia pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſubſpecie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus magis eſt nutrimentum, quàm acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. Ergo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis repraeſentat corpus Chriſti in ratione nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimenti ſpiritualis.</note> 
                  <hi>That the bread with the accidents thereof doth rather repreſent the body of Chriſt by an ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of the bodily ſuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nce with the ſpirituall, then they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>oe by the only accidents.</hi> Thirdly,<note n="e" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Et paulò poſt,</hi> Ponendo panem manere cum ſuis acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus, &amp; corpus Chriſti ibi eſſe verè, pauci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra ponuntur miracula, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ponendo panem ibi eſſe.</note> 
                  <hi>That of the tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation there enſue more inconueniences then of any other opinions.</hi> Fourthly,<note n="f" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rurſus aliquartò poſt.</hi> Mirum videtur quare in vno articulo, qui non eſt principalis articulus fidei, debeat talis intellectus aſſeri, propter quem fides pateat contemptui ſe quentium ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>That it is maruaile</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> an article, which is no principall article of ſayth, they ſhould affirme a ſence or vnderſtanding, by the which the fayth is thruſt foorth for a ſcorne to all thoſe that enſue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> Laſtly,<note n="g" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Sequitur immed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atè.</hi> Nihil eſt tenendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia fidei, niſi quod poteſt extpreſſè haberi de Scriptura, vel expreſſè declaratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt per Eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel euidenter ſequitur ex aliquo planè contento in Scriptura, vel plane de terminato ab Eccleſia, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>That as nothing is to be holden, as of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of fayth, that cannot expreſſely be gathered out of the Scriptures, or that is not expreſſely declared by the Church, or that is not euidently gathered out of matter at full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the Scriptures, or plainely determined by the Church:</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mox.</hi> non caute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non videtur expreſſe haberi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe ibi ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> panis. Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis 6. vbi multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> probatur veritas Euchariſtiae, planum eſt vbi Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it <hi>Ego ſum panis viuus, qui manducauerit ex hoc pane,</hi> &amp;c. Et 1. ad Cor. 11. Pau lus, <hi>Panis quem frangimus, nonne communicatio corporis Chriſti eſt?</hi> nec inuenitur vbi Eccleſia iſtam veritatem determinet ſolenniter; nec etiam qualiter iſtud poſſit ab al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo manifeſte credito euidenter inferri.</note> 
                  <hi>Yet it doth not ſeeme expreſsely ſet downe, that the ſubſtaunce of bread is not in the Sacrament: but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe S.</hi> Paul 1. Corrin. Cap 11. <hi>ſayth, The bread that wee breake, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt? Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9932:12"/>doe we finde where the Church hath ſolemnly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined of this truth, neyther how it may bee inferred of any thing manifeſtly beleeued.</hi> Then doth hee proceede and ground the ſecond opinion vpon the like reaſons: yea and doth earneſtly refell the reaſons of <hi>Thomas</hi> as well againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as for tranſubſtantiation, which is the third. Laſtly, comming to reſolue, he wotteth not almoſt what elſe to ſay, but that;<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Item ſo.</hi> 82. <hi>b lit. E.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tenetur quod nec pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis manet, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra primam o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinionem, nec annihilatur, nec reſoluitur in materiam primam, ſed conuertitur in corpus Chriſti, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Jt is commonly holden that the bread re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth not,</hi> contrary to the firſt opinion: <hi>And is not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taken away, or reſolued into the firſt matter</hi> (namely accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſecond:) <hi>But is conuerted into the body of Chriſt.</hi> And by what reaſon or authority? <hi>Surely</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>this doth</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mox.</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paliter videtur me mouere, quod de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendum eſt, ſicutſancta Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana Eccleſia, ſicut habetur Extra, de haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. Ad obolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nunc aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſa tenet pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiari in corpus, &amp; vinum in ſanguinem, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut manifeſte habetur Extra. de Summa Tri nit. &amp; ſide Cathol. Firmitercredimus, vna vero, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>eſpecially ſeeme to mooue me, that we muſt holde of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, as the holy Church of Rome holdeth, as it is ſet downe Extra. de haereticis. Ad abolendam &amp;c. But ſhe now holdeth that the bread is tranſubſtantiated into the body, &amp; the wine into the bloud, as we haue it manifeſtly ſet downe Extra. de Summa Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. &amp; fide Cath. Firmiter credimus, &amp;c. vna vero;</hi> that is to ſay, in the decree of <hi>Latran.</hi> But what an anſwere heere is to that which was ſo well grounded? That wee muſt held nothing to bee of the ſubſtaunce of fayth. but that which is expreſſely in the Scriptures, or that is taken out of ſome what plainely, <hi>planè,</hi> contayned in the Scriptures, or that hath beene expreſſely declared by the Church? Truely to this argument, <hi>wherin</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>conſiſteth the force,</hi> he hath no more to ſay, but<note n="l" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ibid. lit. G.</hi> Ad tertiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vbi ſtar vis, docendum quod Eccleſia declarauit iſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intellectum eſſe de veritate fidei in ille. Simbolo edito ſub <hi>Innocentio</hi> 3, in Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cilio Laterane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi, Firmiter credimus, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>the Church of God hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this vnderſtanding, or this ſence to be the truth of the faith, in that Creed that was formed vnder</hi> Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>the third in the counſel of Latran, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame we haue in <hi>Reportat.</hi> diſt. 10. q. 1. &amp; diſt. 11. q. 3. for hauing argued vpon the 3. opinions, &amp; with the afore named reaſons fought with tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9932:12"/>he particularly ſaith.<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem Repor, in</hi> 4. <hi>ſentent. d.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>imprime a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Bapt. &amp; Ioan. Bernardu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam.</hi> 1597. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co quod licet ſubſtantia pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis maneret, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auſerret vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que eſſet occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio Idolatriae, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſay that albeit the ſubſtance of bread ſhould remaine, yet could it not aboliſh the worſhip of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, neither be any cauſe of Idolatry, &amp;c.</hi> Againe,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> Dico quod magis ſubſtantia pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cum acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentat corpus Chriſti, quam accidentia tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior ſit conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ad ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, quam ad accident.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſay that the ſubſtance of bread, with the accidents doth better repreſent the body of Chriſt then the accidents onely, &amp;c.</hi> Heere note that theſe words are his owne, and ſo he proceedeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ſimply in theſe words.<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibidan opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nione auctoris.</hi> Teneo conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem, quia Eccleſia tenet, Quia ſides Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſiciet. Et iam ſub <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentio</hi> 3. or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatum fuit tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>I holde the concluſion, becauſe the Church holdeth it: For the faith of S.</hi> Peter <hi>ſhall not fayle, and now vnder</hi> Innocent <hi>the</hi> 3. <hi>it was decreed to be thus holden, &amp;c.</hi> A moſt euidentargument, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reaſon, that the nature of the Sacrament, that the faith proceeding from the Church, yea that the holy Scriptures would haue caried it away otherwiſe, had it not been ſtayed by the deciſion of the counſell of <hi>Latran.</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="bottom">Dominicus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Soto in li. <hi>4.</hi> Senten. d <hi>11</hi> Ioſeph Angels.</note> Conſequently, an argument (as the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> did maintaine) that that which he ſaid, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not ſimply to argue vpon it, but to ſhew what his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution had been, had he not been with-holden with a ſtrong bridle. And indeed (<hi>Dominicus a Soto</hi> (one of their moſt famous Doctors, doth not forbeare to impute vnto <hi>Scot,</hi> that he held but a hard reſolution of tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, as a matter not to bee vpholden by the authority of the Scriptures: And <hi>Joſeph Angles</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="bottom">in floribus Theologi caru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaſtionum, qu eſt. <hi>5.</hi> de conuerſione.</note> a Spaniſh diuine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to defend him. Now vpon the difficulty that our Maſters y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners found in the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they referred the iudgement to an other time, as perceiuing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was no matter of audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Neither may we heer forget one Schoole trick that the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> played the L. of <hi>Pleſ:</hi> for in as much as in <hi>Scots</hi> booke that he had ſent him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer night, hee had noted the places which hee purpoſed to vſe to maintaine his allegation, he brought in an other &amp; of an other print to the table, that he might the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer find it out; which when the ſaid L. told him of, he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for the time to make no account, though afterward he boaſted of it, &amp; the like he did vpon ſundry inſtances.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9932:13"/>
               <head>The ſecond place out of <hi>Durand.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the ſecond,<note place="margin">Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 4. de Eu char. c. 9 edi. 1. p. 870. l. 24. edi. 2. pa. 936. l. 31. edi. 3. p. 764. l. 11.</note> followed a place out of <hi>Durand</hi> of <hi>Porcin</hi> page 870 line 24. in theſe wordes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame matter. <hi>Contrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wiſe</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that the ſubſtances of Bread and wine doe remaine, yet doth there enſue but one difficultie, namely, that two bodies be togither, neither too great, nor indiſsoluble: admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the contrary, we ſhall finde many; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ely, how theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents may bee nouriſhed, bee corrupted, how ſome thing may be engendred, conſidering that all thinges are made of the preſuppoſed matter, and therefore it ſeemeth better to holde to the firſt, &amp;c.</hi> In which place the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> againe pretended, that the Lord of <hi>Pleſſis</hi> had taken <hi>Durands</hi> oppoſition for his reſolution, and at the firſt bluſh with ſome appearaunce, becauſe theſe wordes are ſet downe in the oppoſition. Heerunto the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> aunſwered, that <hi>Durand,</hi> had he not beene with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by the counſell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> did in the deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he made, ſufficiently ſhew what his opinion was in this diſputation of tranſubſtantion; when ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing propounded this multiplicity of inconueniences, hee playnely pronounceth, and can not bee weary of it;<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Durand in</hi> 4 <hi>ſentent. d</hi> 11 <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>fo.</hi> 274. <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar.</hi> 9. <hi>Lugduni a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Gaſp. à Porton. triu</hi> 1.56. Quamuis iſte modus ſit de facto, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt tamen negandum quin alius modus ſit Deo poſſibilis, ita videlicet quod Deus poſſet ſacore, quod remanente ſubſlantia panis &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ini, corpus &amp; ſanguis Chriſti eſſent in hoc Sacramento.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee muſt not deny but there is another meanes poſſible vnto God, the ſubſtaunce of bread and wine ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, albeit this meanes be indeed, &amp;c.</hi> Agayne, Artic. xi. (omitting theſe woordes, <hi>Albeit this meanes bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi>)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9932:13"/>hee repeateth the ſame.<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Item. art.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 75. Non eit tamen negan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quin ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Jt cannot be denyed, &amp;c.</hi> Agayne, Artic. xiiii.<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Item, art.</hi> 14. Satis etiam du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogare videtur imme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ati di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinae pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae, dicere quod Deus non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit facere cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſuum eſſe in ſacramento per alium mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per conuerſionem ſubſtantiae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis in ipſum: maxime cum ponendo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fieri, difficilimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt videre, qualiter ipſa faciat ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ad hoc quod corpus Chriſti ſit in ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Jt is hard and ſeemeth to derogate to the infinite power of God, to ſay that God cannot make his body to be in the Sacrament by any other meanes but by the conuerſion of the ſubſtaunce of bread and wine thereinto, eſpecially conſidering that admitting there bee a connerſion made, yet it is very hard to perceiue after what manner hee doth any thing, that the body of Chriſt may be in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Finally,<note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rurſus paucis interiectis.</hi> Patet ergo quod eſt temerarium dicere quod cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti diuina virtute non poſſit eſſe in ſacramento, niſi per conuerſionem panisin ipſum.</note> 
                  <hi>Jt doth therefore appeare that it is raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to ſay that the body of Chriſt cannot by his Diuyne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be in the Sacrament, but onely by the conuerſion of the bread thereinto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this proceeding, and that ſtil from his owne ſence and not from any other bodies, ſo greatly doth thys new interpretation ſet vpon the wordes of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment torment hys mynde! Then comming to ſhutte vp his opinion, according to the which the bread re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth in the Sacrament, notwithſtanding, the reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without laying away tranſubſtantiation;<note n="e" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non multo poſi. art.</hi> 15. Si iſte modus eſſet verus de facto, multae dub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ationes quae occurrunt circa hoc Sacramentum (tenendo quod ſubſtantia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nis non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emaneat) eſſent ſolutae. Dubitatur enim qualiter ex hoc ſacramento poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> quid nutriri, &amp; quomodo ſpecies poſſunt corrumpi, &amp; ex els aliquid generari: quae omnia ſaluarentur naturaliter eo modo ſicut ſaluarentur, ſi naturae panis &amp; vini non aſſumerentur ad naturam ſacramenti: ponuntur enim man ere poſt conſecrationem, ſicut ante.</note> 
                  <hi>If thys meanes</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>were indeed true, many difficultyes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning in the Sacrament, by holding that the ſubſtaunce of bread remaineth not, ſhould bee reſolued: for it is doubted after what manner any thing can bee nouriſhed of this Sacrament: alſo how the formes may be corrupted, and how of the ſame any thing may be engendred. All which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9932:14"/>difficulties might naturally be ſalued by this meanes, euen as they might be ſalued if the natures of bread and wine were not taken or imployed for the nature of the Sacrament: For by this meanes we doe admit that they doe remaine after the conſecration as before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Stil ſpeaking in his owne ſence. Wherin we are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to note, that in his concluſion, and ſpeaking in hys owne perſon, hee repeateth the ſame woordes that wee read in the oppoſition formed in the name of a thyrd. Becauſe theſe difficultyes, wherein hee findeth no ſufficient ſolution, doe ſticke in hys ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke. And in the ende, howe dooth hee ſatiſfie hymſelfe? Surely euen as <hi>Scot</hi> hath before done.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et in fine ar.</hi> 15. Sed quia hic modus non debet teneri de facto, cum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauerit oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum, quçnon preſumitur er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare in talibus, ideo tenendo de facto aliam partem, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondendum eſt ad argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta quae ſunt in contrarium.</note> 
                  <hi>But</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>in as much as this meanes muſt not bee holden in deed, becauſe the Church hath determined the contrary:</hi> (Namely in the counſel of <hi>Latran</hi>) <hi>which it is to be preſumed doth not erre in ſuch matter, therefore it is that indeed holding the other part, we muſt anſwere to the arguments that are to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> And this is the anſwere that he maketh;<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> art.</hi> 16. In his quae ſunt fidei non ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eligendum eſt eillud ad quod ſequu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pauciores diſſicultates, &amp;c. Sed eſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magis illud quod eſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dictis ſanctorum, &amp; tradicioni Eccleaſiaſticae.</note> 
                  <hi>We muſt not alwaies ſtand vpon the ſence that bringeth feweſt inconueniences, but vpon the ſame that beſt agreeeth with the ſayings of the Saints, and the Eccleſiaſticall traditions.</hi> He is wiſe enough for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the tenure of the holy Scriptures, or with the nature of the Sacrament. And indeed the Lord of <hi>Eur.</hi> ſhould haue learned of his <hi>Bellarmin</hi> that <hi>Durand</hi> dyd not ſufficiently beleeue tranſubſtantiation, who in his 3. booke of the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, Chap. xi. hath theſe words.<note n="h" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Bellarm. de Sacram. Euchar. lib.</hi> 3. c. 11 Durandus docuit parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſentialem, id eſt forma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis conuerti; partem altera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, id eſt materia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non conuerti.</note> 
                  <hi>Durand hath taught that an eſſential part of the bread, namely the forme, is conuerted, and that the other part, namely the ſubſtance, is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted.</hi> Which he doth expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9932:14"/>confute in the 13. Chapter of his third booke, and citeth <hi>Durand</hi> vpon the 4. booke of ſentences Diſt. 11. q. 3. Heere would our Maſters and Commiſſioners haue referred the iudgement, as they had done with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; confeſſing that the whole queſtion deſerued to be read, that it might be iudged by the courſe thereof. But then the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> found himſelfe agreeued, ſaying that it was in vaine for them to diſpute, if they wold not iudge; ſundry tymes ſpeaking to the King to appoynt his pleaſure to the ſayd Commiſſioners. Whereupon his Maieſty comming vnto them, this Article was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided and the Lord Chauncellor pronounced <hi>That</hi> Durands <hi>oppoſition was alleaged for his reſolution.</hi> Heere let the reader iudge, albeit it were ſo, of the wordes of the oppoſition, ſo playnely repeated in the reſolution: and <hi>Durand</hi> ſpeaking no longer in a third perſon, but in his owne perſon, afterward likewiſe theſe clauſes, <hi>Durum eſt, Temerarium eſt: Jt is hard, It is raſh, &amp;c.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſo doubtfull, ſo tickliſh, ſo problematticall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> might pretend any haynous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes, euen palpably to be iudged at the very opening of the booke, at the bare ſight thereof, where a mans iudgement, not his eyes, is in daunger of fayling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third place out of Chriſoſtom <hi>vpon the firſt to the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the third, they came to a place of <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> vpon the firſt to the <hi>Theſsa.</hi> Hom. 1.<note place="margin">Liu 3 de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. chap. 11. ed. 1. pa. 5. 7. l. 31. edit. 2. p. 538. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ed. 3, p. 498. l. 22.</note> alleaged by the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> in his booke p. 537. li. 31. where hee examineth all the places of Scripture, which the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries doe boldely apply to the inuocation of Saints,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9932:15"/>namely this out of <hi>Ieremy.</hi> 15.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem. c.</hi> 15. <hi>v</hi> 1. Si ſtererint <hi>Moyſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, non eſt anima mea ad popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum iſtum.</note> 
                  <hi>Though</hi> Samuell <hi>and</hi> Moyſes <hi>ſhould ſtand before me, yet ſhould not my affection be to this people.</hi> In which place hauing prooued by S. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eroſme, Theodoret,</hi> S. <hi>Gregory, Hugo Cardinall,</hi> yea the gloſſe it ſelfe, that this place is meant of, the interceſſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuell</hi> when they liued, betweene the wrath of God and the ſinnes of the people; But not of any interceſſion of the dead Saintes vnto God for the faythfull liuing heere beneath; hee withall addeth, that heere of <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> gathereth a concluſion cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that of the aduerſaries: namely, <hi>That wee muſt not ſtand vpon the Prayers of the Saints, but worke our ſaluation with feare and trembling.</hi> Now againſt this place the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> pretended two thinges. The one, that the Lord of <hi>Pleſſes</hi> had cut him off in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall wordes: namely, <hi>if we be negligent.</hi> The other that <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> entreated of the interceſſion of the Saints deceaſed, which the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> denyed. To the firſt the Lord of <hi>Pleſſes</hi> aunſwered, that he alleadged not the expreſſe wordes of <hi>Chriſoſtom,</hi> but onely ſet downe the ſence, becauſe the diſcourſe contayned twoo or three whole pages, which he reduced as it were into a Theſes: and that indeed he alleaged it, after the phraſe of the Gramarians, <hi>Oratione obliqua non recta.</hi> in an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart and not direct ſpeech, by this word, <hi>That he, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore that he was not bound to the courſe of the text. To the other, that in this allegation he had no other purpoſe but to ſhew that <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> out of this place of <hi>Ieremy</hi> had not gathered, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day doth, the interceſſion and inuocation of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Saintes: but contrariwiſe had collected this Doctrine; That wee muſt not generally ſtand vpon the prayers of the Saintes, whether aliue or dead, in ſomme vpon other mens prayers; but that we muſt watch, pray,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9932:15"/>and endeuour (as the Apoſtle ſayth) <hi>to make ſure our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation with feare and trembling.</hi> And indeed that this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent appeared in theſe words;<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtan</hi> 1. <hi>ad Theſſal. chap.</hi> 1. <hi>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1. <hi>ſub fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> p.</hi> 1414 <hi>editionts Groe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Lat. Hier. Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melini</hi> 1596. Et vt id ſeras. audi Deum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem. Si ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terint <hi>Noe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iob</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel,</hi> non eripient fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios ſuos, &amp; fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, &amp; ruiſus. Si ſteterit <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Samuel.</hi> Et vide quomodo hoc dicitur du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obus Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis: quoniam ambo pro ipſis togarant &amp; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> era<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſequuti, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>And to the end thou ſhouldeſt know</hi> (namely that the prayers of the Saints doe not profit, except we doe conuert and turne vnto God.) <hi>hear what the Lord ſaith by the Prophet; If</hi> Noè, Iob, &amp; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel <hi>ſtood before me, yet ſhould they not ſaue their Sonnes nor their Daughters.</hi> And againe, <hi>Jf</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Samuel, <hi>&amp;c. And marke how this is ſpoken to two Prophets, becauſe both of them had prayed, but had not obtained, &amp;c.</hi> Thus that this place of <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> was not curtalled, neyther could be, ſith it was but touched by the way and not alleaged: Much leſſe was it wreſted to any contrary ſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe generally he ſpeaketh of the prayers of the Saints, albeit the examples were of thoſe that are yet conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with vs heere beneath.</p>
               <p>Now for the better opening of this point, the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> owne words did ſuffice, <hi>That we muſt not ſtand vpon.</hi> For what is it to ſtand vpon, but wholy to truſt, or to relye vpon, euen to the excluſion of our owne duety and of all other meanes? Hee did then expreſſe the meaning of <hi>Chriſoſtom,</hi> that the prayers of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, of the Saints, of the faithfull, each for other are good, are to bee wiſhed: But that we ſhould not ſleepe vpon them; but for our owne parts doe our duetyes: Alſo the courſe of the text will lead vs thereunto.<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et pa.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Nullus dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, nullus ſit piger ad virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Hoc enim eſt ſomnus. Neſcitis quando dormimus, quam noſtra non ſunt in tuto, quam faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le eis parentur inſidiae? Quando aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vigilamus non opus eſt nobis tanta cuſtodia, Quando dormimus, etiam cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multa cuſtodia, ſepe perimus. Sunt &amp; oſtea, &amp; vectes, &amp; cuſtodes, &amp; vigiles; &amp; tamen fur ingreditur. Cur haec dico? Quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi vigilemus non egebimus alioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auxilio. Sin autem dormiamus, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multum nobis prodeſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auxilium, ſed etiam cum illo perimus.</note> 
                  <hi>Let no man</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>lull himſelfe on ſleep, let no man bee ſlow to vertue; for that is a ſleeping. Know you not when we ſleep,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9932:16"/>how ſmall aſſuraunce we haue, how eaſie a matter it is to rob vs? and contrariwiſe when wee watch, there need no ſuch guarde: When wee ſle pe, not withſtanding all our guard, wee many times perriſh; VVe baue gates, barres, boulter, watchmen and ſentinels, yet doth the theefe ſometimes get in: VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſay all this? becauſe if we watch, we ſhall not neede the helpe of others; but contrariwiſe, if we ſleep, the help of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhall ſtand vs in ſmall ſteed, but wee ſhall periſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall.</hi> Of others ſaith he in generall: and what mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he by others?<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sequiter im mediatè.</hi> Bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt frui Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum precibus, ſed eum ipſi quoque fueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus intenti o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peri.</note> 
                  <hi>Je is good</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>to haue the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Sayntes, but alwaies prouided that our ſelues bee attentiue to our owne workes.</hi> And did not the Lord of <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſsis</hi> ſay as much? <hi>Not to depend vpon the prayers of the Saints, but to make ſure our ſaluation with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</hi> And therefore with what conſcience can it bee ſayd that this place is curtalled? as indeed our Maſters the Commiſſioners did not ſo iudge. Now for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of the ſecond, whether this place of <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> doth commend vnto vs the inuocation of the dead Saints, wee muſt conſider what followeth.<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mox imme diatè.</hi> Et quid mihi, inquit, opus eſt alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum precibus, cum ſuero in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus operi? Ne te eo redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas vt opus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas. Nec ego quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoc vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ſed op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſemper h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>be mus, ſi ſapia mus.</note> 
                  <hi>And what need I</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>aliorum precibus, the prayers of others, ſo long as my ſelfe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e labour? Now</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>euer bring thy ſelfe into that neceſsity, neyther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it my minde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ou ſhouldeſt: yet if we be wiſe we doe alwaies ſtand in need.</hi> But of what Saints? of the dead, or of the faythfull that liue? ſurely there is enough ſpoken of that: neyther doe wee doubt but the Saynts that tryu nph with Chriſt, doe pray for the Church milirant heere beneath. But wee are not come to that. For that they pray for the aduauncement of Gods kingdome, or for our perticuler neceſſityes; that they pray according to theyr charity that quayleth not: or that we may in fayth pray to them, haning no foundation therfore, are very contrary queſtions. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit heere wee ſhall ſee that <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> ſpeaketh or the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9932:16"/>prayers of the Saintes that are conuerſant among vs, grounded vpon the expreſſe word of God, of whome (ſayth he) we ſtand in need; and yet doth he exhort vs not to relye vpon them.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sequitur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatè.</hi> Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dicebat, Quid mihi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, etiamſi qui precaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur non era<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tco digni, imó verò ne pares quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Et tu dices; Quid mihi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus? Petrus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dixit, Quid mihi opus eſt precibus? Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio enim, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, fiebat ſine intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ab Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia ad Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro eo.</note> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> Paul (ſayth he) <hi>ſaid not what need I prayers? albeit they that prayed were not worthy, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther equall with him: yet thou ſaieſt what need J prayers? Neither did S.</hi> Peter <hi>likewiſe ſay, what need I prayers? for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the church doth make prayers for him without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion; &amp;c.</hi> Many other exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples he doth alſo alleage. Thus farre then for the Saintes that pray heere beneath for the faithfull, deſiring all good men to haue care of them in theyr prayers, which (ſayth he) are of efficacy with God. But how? ioyned with our owne, with the duety that we performe in our vocation: according to that which the Apoſtle ſayth.<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et pa.</hi> 1417. <hi>ex</hi> 1 <hi>ad Cor. cap.</hi> 1. Adiuua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus &amp; vopis in oratione pro nobis. Vt Ex multis perſonis eius qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis eſt donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis per mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s gratiae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur pro nobis.</note> 
                  <hi>That yee labour together in prayers for vs, that for the gift beſtowed vpon vs for many, thankes may begiuen by many perſons for vs.</hi> Neyther may we heere forget, that when in this aſſiſtance they heard ſpeaking of liuing Saints, it was newes vnto them, as if it were not a common matter, both in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and in the Fathers, to terme the faythfull, Saintes, euen in this life: not for that they are canonized by the Pope, but ſanctified by fayth in the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt. Yer vpon this ignoraunce they made ſundry ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d th he not heere ſpeake expreſſely of the prayers of the Saints deceaſed for the liuing? Doth hee not exhort the faithfull aliue to inuocate the dead, to relye vpon they ſuffiages, vpon theyr paſſions or vpon their merites?<note n="h" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Et aliquantò poſt. ex</hi> 4. <hi>Re. ca</hi> 19. Audi Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui que dicente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Protegan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hanc ciuita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em prop er me, &amp; propter <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeruum meum. Sed quando? Tempore <hi>Ezechiae</hi> quierat iuſtus, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Surely</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>God ſaid, I will protect
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9932:17"/>this Citty for my owne ſake, and for my ſeruaunt Dauids ſake.</hi> Namely, becauſe of my couenant in free mercy, that I haue made with <hi>Dauid</hi> and with his ſeede. <hi>But when? Jn the daies of</hi> Ezechias, <hi>who was righteous.</hi> Againe,<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et in ſine ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pag.</hi> 1413 Audi Deum dicentem de amice. <hi>Iobi;</hi> Et orabit; inquit, pro vobis, &amp; dimittetur vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis peccatum quoniam pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carunt quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed non mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num admiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant peccatum. Sed hic ipſe iuſtus qui per preces tunc ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauit ſuos ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos in tempore Iudaico, non potuit ſeruare Iudaeos pereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies. Et vt id ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, audi Deum dicentem per Prophetam; Si ſteteris <hi>Noe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iob,</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel;</hi> non eripient fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios ſuos &amp; fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</note> 
                  <hi>And</hi> Iob <hi>(ſaith the Lord) ſhall pray for you.</hi> (Namely, he liuing for his liuing friendes) <hi>and your ſinnes ſhall bee remitted: But the ſame righteous</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that ſaued his friends by his prayers, in the dayes of the Jewes, cannot ſaue the Jewes. And that thou maiſt be the better enformed thereof, heare the Lord, who ſayth: Jf</hi> Noah, Iob <hi>and</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel <hi>ſtood before me, &amp;c.</hi> And out of this place did the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> argue when he ſpake of the Saintes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed. But by that which followeth, it ſhall moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare that he meaneth, if they had been eyther to returne in the dayes of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> or if they had been in his place; and ſo did the Fathers vnderſtand it. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> in the ſame place, ſoone after in expreſſe tearmes ſayth.<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> p.</hi> 1. 1414. Si ſteterit <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> &amp;c. qui dixit, Si demittas quidem peccatum, dimitte; ſin minus, me quoque dele. Si hîc er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go nunc eſſet, &amp; haec diceret non impetraret. Et ſi rurſus <hi>Samuel,</hi> &amp;c. Si iſti ergo ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terint nihil proficient.</note> 
                  <hi>Jf</hi> Moſes <hi>himſelfe</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>were now heere, and ſhould ſay vnto me for the people as heeretofore, If thou wilt not forgiue them, blot me out, hee ſhould not bee heard. Alſo if</hi> Samuel <hi>likewiſe: alſo if theſe,</hi> (Namely <hi>Noah, Iob</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi>) <hi>they ſhould not preuaile:</hi> that is to ſay, comming here downe and making interceſſion as thou doſt: leaſt thou ſhouldſt thinke my denyall vnto thee, were in regard of thy perſon:<note n="l" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Sequitur immediate.</hi> Et dicit de <hi>Noe,</hi> Iuſtus perfectus in generatione ſua. Et de <hi>Iob.</hi> Irreprehenſibilis, iuſtus, verus, pius.</note> Noah <hi>neuertheleſſe</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>and</hi> Iob <hi>and</hi> Daniel <hi>righteous men, irreprehenſible, full of godlines, &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay, Saintes. But if the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> would reply, but to what purpoſe is this that he ſpeaketh of the liuing, againſt the inuocation of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9932:17"/>Saints deceaſed? Surely becauſe with greater reaſon he might haue ſpoken that of the prayers of the Saintes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, which hee ſpake of the liuing: Theſe that are grounded vpon commandement, vpon example, &amp; vpon promiſe: thoſe that haue no ground at all, becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the abuſe ſuppreſſed in theſe were of the greater force alſo againſt them. In the ende <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> concludeth his Homely in theſe wordes.<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mox.</hi> Cum haec ergo ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, neque preces ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namus, neque totum in eas coniiciamus, tum ne pigri ſimus &amp; ſocor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, temerè &amp; inſidiis circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniamur, tum ne a magnolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cro excidamus: ſed &amp; horte mur ad oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; ad manus pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis porrige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>das; &amp; ipſi virtutem ſectemur.</note> 
                  <hi>And therefore knowing theſe things, let vs not contemne the prayers of the Saintes, neyther yet wholy relye vpon them: partly leaſt we ſhould bee ſlouthfull, and ſuffer our ſelues raſhly to be intangled in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhes: partly alſo leaſt wee ſhould incurre ſome great loſſe:</hi> (namely, the aſſiſtaunce of the prayers of the Saintes or faythfull) <hi>but let vs exhort them to pray, and to lift vp theyr handes for vs:</hi> where note, <hi>let vs exhort,</hi> which cannot bee meant but of the liuing, <hi>and our ſelues alſo enſue vertue.</hi> Of the Saintes in the concluſion, as in the promiſes, of the faythfull praying for S. <hi>Paul,</hi> for S. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c. of our ſelues praying heere beneath the one for the other. For whence ſhould the concluſion grow but from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? And thus, how farre is he from exhorting vs to call vpon the Saintes deceaſed, or to truſt to theyr me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits? Had our Maſters the Commiſſioners had time to haue read ouer the whole place at length, as the Lord of <hi>Pleſſis</hi> did moſt earneſtly requeſt; would they haue ſtayed vpon that which the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> did vrge?<note n="n" place="margin">In princi. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>1414.</hi>
                  </note> Iob <hi>in tempore Iudaico non potuit ſeruare Iudaeos pereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> Iob <hi>in the daies of the Iewes, could not ſaue the Iewes that periſhed;</hi> Would they not by that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed haue noted that he aluded to the place of <hi>Ieremy; If</hi> Noah, Daniel <hi>and</hi> Iob <hi>ſtood afore me, &amp;c. Si ſteterint</hi> Noe, Daniel <hi>&amp;</hi> Iob, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Would they not haue perceiued that <hi>Siſteterint</hi> ſignified, if they were in place where thou art O <hi>Jeremy,</hi> when he ſaith; <hi>Siſteterit</hi> Moſes <hi>primus legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9932:18"/>&amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>Sihic ergomure eſſet, &amp;c. Et ſirurſus</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, <hi>&amp;c. If Moſes the firſt law-giuer, &amp;c. Jf be were now lecre, &amp;c. And if againe</hi> Samuel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is to ſay, in the place where thou art. And ſo conſequently would they haue iudged that <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> in this place, ſpake of prayer to the Saintes deceaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth place out of Chriſoſtom <hi>vpon Mathew.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw followeth another of the like nature,<note place="margin">Liu. 3, de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. c. 13. adit. 1. pa. 574. l. 16. edi. 2 p. 617. l. 1. edi. 3, p. 507. l. 39.</note> taken out of the page 574. line 16. where the Lord of <hi>Pleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> ſayth as followeth. Chriſoſtom <hi>ſeemeth to haue tasked himſelfe to beat downe this abuſe, ſo carefull is he to vndermine the foundations vpon euery occaſion.</hi> (Namely, the inuocation of Saintes deceaſed, founded vpon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended merites of others.) <hi>He perceaued</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>that the people truſted more to the helpe of other mens prayers, then to the amendment of their owne liues: And therefore fighteth againſt this opinion.</hi> (Namely, to depend vpon any other whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.) <hi>But</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi>) <hi>we haue much more aſſuraunce through our owne prayers, then through the prayers of others, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth God ſo ſoone graunt our ſaluation at others intreatie, as at our owne: For ſo tooke he compaſsion of the woman of</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan; <hi>gaue faith to the Adultreſſe, and Paradice to the Theefe; and thereto neuer entreated at the interceſsion of eyther aduocate or mediator.</hi> Againſt this place the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded falſehood by omiſſion: Namely, becauſe the Lord of <hi>Pleſsas</hi> had omitted theſe words following;<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chrian Mat. hom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. pag.</hi> 59 <hi>edit. Baſi. apud Froben.</hi> 1558. Et haec non eò dicimus vt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicandum eſſe ſanctis nege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed ne torpeamus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſupini ipſi &amp; dormieates, alus tatum mo do noſtra cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Neyther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e we ſpeake this to denie that wee ſhould pray to Saints, but that wee ſhould not be negligent or ſlouthfull, and ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lling on ſleepe, or being benummed, we ſhould commit the managing of our affaires to others.</hi> Where wee are to note
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9932:18"/>by the way, that the coppy which <hi>Chemnicius</hi> cyteth hath theſe wordes; <hi>Non quod negemus ſanctus orare debere pro peccatoribus; Not that wee deny that the Saints ſhould pray for ſinners.</hi> Where by the ſence ſhould differ very much; &amp; in this caſe hee would not haue made ſuch haſt to taxe him for omiſſion becauſe hee ſhould haue gained no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereby. But taking law of the common leſſon; eyther S. <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> in this Homely ſpeaketh of praying to the liuing Saintes, to remember vs in theyr prayers; eyther elſe of inuocation of the Saints deceaſed. If of theſe, then doth the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> confeſſe the omiſſion, and graunteth that hee hath done amiſſe. If of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, what wrong hath he done, ſith they both agree, for there is no controuerſie in the matter? But ſurely it is moſt euident by the whole courſe of all the Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by the examples produced, that hee there ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely of the holy men that make interceſſion heere beneath in theyr prayers, to God for his people, and of the faythfull praying each for other. In this Homely doth S <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> handle this poynt, that euen our Lords bretheren belieued not in him. And thereout ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth this concluſion; That it is in vaine to haue any familiarity, eyther of Country, Family or Parentage with the Lord, vnleſſe wee labour to conforme our ſelues vnto him. And therefore he ſayth,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 54. Nemo de ſe deſperet, &amp;c. neevila in re a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia ſpem ſuam, quam poſt Dei miſericordiam in vertute ſua collocet.</note> 
                  <hi>Let no man ſettle his hope in any thing, but next vnto the mercy of God, in his owne vertue.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe he alleageth;<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et mox.</hi> Nam &amp; propheta id ipſum ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficans ait, Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter non redimet homo?</note> 
                  <hi>Frater non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimit, redimet homo? The brother redeemeth not, man ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Et pag.</hi> 55. Etiamſi inquit, <hi>Moſes</hi> adeſſet atque <hi>Samuel</hi> tamen corum pro talibus deprecantium, non reciperem orationem.</note> 
                  <hi>Now</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>albeit</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Samuel <hi>were preſent and ſhould pray for that people, yet would I not receaue their prayers.</hi> Like wiſe the more plainely to ſhew
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9932:19"/>vs, that hee ſpeaketh of thoſe men, returning into the eſtate of this life.<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> paulo poſt;</hi> Et ſi <hi>Samuel</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mſum pro ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo indigno deprecetur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ntinuo ad ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m diect Deus Ne lugeas pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter Saul. Eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi pro ſoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quupiam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cur o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauerit, audiet quod <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>And if</hi> Samuell (ſayth hee) <hi>ſhould pray againe for any vnworthy perſon, God would ſtrayght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſay vnto him; Mourne not for</hi> Saul: <hi>Likewiſe if one ſhould pray vnreaſonably for his Siſter, beholde heere what aunſwere was made vnto</hi> Moſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then dooth hee adde,<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sequitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>;</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent enim vim pro nobis, &amp; quidem maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, orationes ſupplicationes quae Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed tune cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nos quoque poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam egeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res reddemur.</note> 
                  <hi>For the prayers and ſupplications of the Saintes for vs are of great force, but when our ſelues alſo doe repent and amend.</hi> And of what Saintes? That ſhall indeede ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that which immediatly followeth.<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sequiter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatè.</hi> Nam etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> qui ſratrem ſuum, &amp; ſexcenta illa milia armatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à tam dira liberauit ira, ſorrem tamen ſuam nequiuit eripere, non quippe erat aequale pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum: Illa enim iniurioſius de <hi>Moſe</hi> fuerat quidda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> locuta, illic vero impietas erat quod perpetratum erat.</note> 
                  <hi>For</hi> Moſes <hi>himſelfe</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>who deliuered his brother and his</hi> 600000. <hi>armed men from the fearefull wrath of God: could not neuert heleſſe warrant his Siſter, albeit the ſinne were not equally alike, for ſhe had ſpoken iniuriouſly of</hi> Moſes: <hi>and on the others behalfe the ſinne that had been committed, was meere impiety:</hi> Then was it of the liuing Saints, &amp; of the faithfull that praye for the ſinnes each of other. There alſo followe many other examples of the like nature: Of <hi>Samuel</hi> praying and being heard for <hi>Iſraell:</hi> praying alſo, but not heard, for <hi>Saul.</hi> Of <hi>Jeremy</hi> heard when he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſome: and when hee prayed for the people, not heard: Of <hi>Daniel</hi> praying for the people, and not heard: and heard when he prayed for the Heathen, &amp;c.<note n="h" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Et in fine eiuſd. pag.</hi> 55. Equibus proſecto redolet, quod ſi negligentes fuerimus ac deſides, nec per alioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quidem poterimus merita ſaluati. Sin vero ſobriè agemus, etiam per noſmetipſos iſtud valeamus eſſicere, &amp; multo magis per nos quam per alios. Nam &amp; Deus gratiam non tam aliis roga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus pro nobis. vult donare, quam nobis: quo &amp; fruamur libertate Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landi, &amp; emendemur, dum ipſi ſtudemus Deum reconciliare.</note> 
                  <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>wee doe learne that if our ſelues be ſlouthfull
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9932:19"/>and negligent, we cannot be ſaued, no not by the merds of others: But if wee ſiue ſoberly, wee may by our ſelues, and much rather by our ſelues then by others: For God will alſo ſhew mercy not ſo much for then ſakes that pray for vs, as for our owne; that wee might vſe the libertie of ſpeaking with God, and labouring to recencile our ſelues to him, might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, &amp;c.</hi> Which againe he prooueth by the example of the Cananite, of the euill liuing woman: of the theefe, &amp;c.<note n="i" place="margin">Sic Chananae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am illa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do miſeratus eſt: ſic etiam meretrici do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauit ſalutem, ſic latro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo mediatore intercedente.</note> 
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o whome</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>God gaue ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not that any Patron or Mediator made interceſsion for them.</hi> Where then hytherto, where is any other inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or interceſſion, other then the liuing Saintes? not one word of the deceaſed. Now doe immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the wordes now in queſtion, &amp; let vs take them euen as he liſt.<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sequitur im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatè.</hi> Et haec non eo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus, vt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicandum eſſe Sanctis nege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed ne torpeamus, neveſupini ipſi &amp; dormietes aliis, tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>odo noſtra curanda mandemus.</note> 
                  <hi>But we ſpeake not theſe thinges to denye that we ſhould pray to the Saints, but that we ſhould beware that we ſuffer not our ſelues to be ouertaken with ſlouth and careleſſenes: and ſo falling on ſleep, commit the mannaging of our matters to others.</hi> And then as in all other places, the liuing Saintes, not the deceaſed. Heere will the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> ſay againe. Why ſhould he alleage this place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the inuccation of Saintes deceaſed, ſith heere is no mention but of the prayers of the liuing Saintes? Surely becauſe he meant to vndermine the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of that confidence, that men doe repoſe in the holyneſſe and merites of others: as alſo, as wee ſayd before, that if wee may not repoſe our ſelues vpon the prayers of thoſe that doe conuerſe with vs, whoſe conditions we doe know, and they ours; and to whom in charity we are commended by the Lord, and they to vs: much leſſe vpon the prayers of thoſe that reſt aboue (as ſaith Saint <hi>John</hi>) from all their labours; who (ſayth S. <hi>Anguſtine</hi> vnto vs) doe not inter meddle
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9932:20"/>with the affayres of this world: the meaſure of whoſe knowledge we know not, as likewiſe they knewe not the perticular neceſſities of our conditions. Otherwiſe, ſhould they not be Gods? Whereof moreouer we haue neyther in the Olde Teſtament, nor in the New, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commaundement, example or promiſe: Whereas the prayers of the Saintes conuerſant heere among vs, one for an other, ſtand both vpon expreſſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement and ordinary practiſe. All which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſentence paſſed for the omiſſion: that theſe words, <hi>Et haec non eo dicimus vt ſupplicandum ſanctis eſſe negemus: Neither doe J ſpeake theſe thinges to deny that we ſhould pray vnto Saintes, &amp;c.</hi> ought to haue beene added, for the ground-worke; that this Homely is to be vnderſtood of Saintes deceaſed. And all for want of reading the Text throughout, as the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> inſtantly required: but the common error carried it away, as if there had neuer been mention of any other Sayntes but of the deceaſed. As if <hi>Caris Dei adgeniculari; Sanctorum vincula deoſculari; To kneele to the beloued of God; To kiſſe the bondes of the Saintes,</hi> in <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and a thouſand ſuch other places in the Fathers, could be vnderſtood of others, then thoſe that are conuerſant heere beneath among vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9932:20"/>
               <head>The fifth place out of <hi>Hieromy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw followeth the fifth taken out of S. <hi>Hierom</hi> vpon <hi>Ezechiel</hi> lib. 4. Ca. 14.<note place="margin">Lib. 3. of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uchar. ch. 14. edir. 1. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. l. 8. edit. 2. p. 626. l. 15. edit. 3. p. 502 l. 16.</note> alleaged by the L. of <hi>Pleſsis.</hi> p. 583. li. 8. againſt prayers to Saintes, in theſe words.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Haerony in Ezechiele lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>ex edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Chriſt. Plantini</hi> 1578. Quod ſi in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo fiducia eſt inſolo domino conſidamus. Maledictus .n. omnis homo qui ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habet in homine, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uis ſancti ſint, quamuis Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, Legimus Nolite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidere in homimbus. <hi>Et iterum.</hi> Bo num eſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere in Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no quam co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pibus. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in, princip ibus tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcaeculi, ſed &amp; in principibus Eccleaſiarum, qui ſuas ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ium aoimas ſi iuſti ſuerint, liberabun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Filios autem ac ſilias quos in Eccleſia genuetint, ſi fuerint negligentes, ſaiuare non poterunt.</note> 
                  <hi>If truſt</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>bee to bee repoſed in any, let vs repoſe our truſt in one only God; for curſed is the man that truſteth in men, be they Saints, be they Prophets. Wee muſt not truſt Principtbus Eccleſiarum, in the Principles of the Church, who albeit they bee righteous, ſhall deliuer but their owne ſoules, not the ſoules of their children.</hi> Againſt this place alſo the L. of <hi>Eureux</hi> pleaded omiſſion, becauſe theſe word. <hi>(Sinegligentes fuerint, if they be negligent)</hi> were omitted. Which the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> conſeſſeth to be true (as he will alwaies do, where like matter failes our) not of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bad intent, for what ſhould he get by it? but becauſe (as it ſeemeth) he relyed vpon the aduerſaries owne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation. For in their ordinary gloſſe, euen vpon this very place of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> this place is alleaged, and theſe very wordes omitted; and as we may well thinke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraude.<note n="b" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ny. in Gloſſa ordinaria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>duni</hi> 159<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>in illuel Ezec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ielis c.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Non uberabunt fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>euaefiuas, &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onum eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce fidere in Domino, quam confidere in principibus. &amp;c. Non ſecul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tantum, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> iuſti ruerint tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animas ſuas liberabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> finos vel fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as, quos in Eccleſia genueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> 
                  <hi>It is good</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to truſt in the Lord, rather then to truſt in Princes, not of the world onely, but euen of the Churches: who albeit they be righteous, ſhall deliuer but theyr owne ſoules, not their Sonnes nor their daughters, whom they haue begotten in the Church.</hi> Alſo this place of <hi>Ezechul</hi> doth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9932:21"/>S. <hi>Hierome</hi> vnder-ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in like ſence, as <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> doth the place of <hi>Noah, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> returning into this world. Heere againe did the L. of <hi>Eureux</hi> inſtantly vrge; what maketh this place againſt the inuocation of Saintes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, ſith it ſpeaketh properly of the liuing? Whereto he was anſwered as in the former; but the rather, becauſe in the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> booke, entreating vpon this place of S. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rame</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> enſued theſe words that anſwered him.<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Obſeurch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, docentur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> haue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>lam nou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> quod lautat. Deum in praeſenti ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo ſumus, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue orationibus, ſiue conſiliis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſe nos coadiunari. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> autem ante tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal Chriſti, venerimus, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ob,</hi> non <hi>Daeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> nec <hi>Noe</hi> ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare poſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quoquam; ſed vnumquem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que portare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nusſuum.</note> 
                  <hi>And to the end we ſhould not thinke that he meant not to ſpeake but of the liuing, writing vpon the Epiſtle to the</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians <hi>vpon theſe words; Euery man ſhould beare his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, marke what he ſaith: By this ſhort ſentence we doe learne, albeit darkely, a new Doctrine that is hidden, that ſo long as we remaine in this world, wee may bee holpen by the prayers and counſailes one of an other; But when wee come before the Tribunall ſeate of Chriſt, neither</hi> Iob, <hi>nor</hi> Daniel, <hi>nor</hi> Noah, <hi>can pray for any man, but euery man ſhal beare his owne bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi> Now the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> vrged him to way theſe words; <hi>ſiue orationibus, ſiue conſiliis: Whether with prayer, or with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell:</hi> But he would not heare him, ſaying hee had not to doe but with this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſixt place out of <hi>S. Cirill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſixt was a place out of S. <hi>Cirill</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in his ſixt booke againſt <hi>Iulian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2 de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 3. ed. 1. p. 233. l 5. edit. 2. p. 239. l. 30. ed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 139. l. 25.</note> taken out of the pa. 223. l. 5. where the L. of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> ſayth. <hi>That he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth the Emperour</hi> Iulian, <hi>who obiected the honour done to the Croſſe; That the chriſtians doe yeeld neither adoration nor reuerence to the ſigne of the Croſſe.</hi> Ouer largely peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the words, though ſurely not for the ſence. And therefore the L of <hi>Eur.</hi> pretending vntruth, grounded
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9932:21"/>vpon theſe wordes; <hi>He anſwereth,</hi> becauſe he anſwereth not preciſely in theſe wordes. Heereto the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that by his owne text it appeared, that he neuer meant to alleage the wordes of <hi>Cirill,</hi> onely hee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſence out of a diſcourſe, of a leafe in quantity: that indeed the oration was not direct, but by the way, the Character of the text, not of any allegation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that they ought to ſeeke the ſence and not the wordes: and the rather becauſe it hath been often ſayd, that the vntruth ſhould not be concluded vpon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of woords, in caſe the ſence were to be found. And as for the ſence, ſayth hee, <hi>Julian</hi> ſayd vnto the Chriſtians.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cirill. Alena. contra Iulianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 134. <hi>to.</hi> 3. <hi>Baſill. apud Ioan. Heruagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi> 1566. Et ô miſerihomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, cum ſerue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur arma qure magnus demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit Iupiter, hoc eſt, pater Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, pignore da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to non verbo, ſed re, quod ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatem noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram perpettio protecturusſit, ceſſatis adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; colere &amp; interim crucis lignum adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, imagines illius in fronte &amp; antedomus pingentes.</note> 
                  <hi>Yee wretches as yee are, yee worſhip not Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia de coelo lapſa, &amp; our bucklers fallen from heauen, which</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter <hi>hath giuen vs for the protection of our Citty, and yet yee worſhip the tree of the Croſse, and paint the Images thereof in the forefronts, and before your houſes.</hi> Heereunto if the Chriſtians in thoſe daies had worſhipped the tree of the Croſſe, what was there to be ſaid, ſauing, we worſhip it becauſe it deſerueth worſhip, and not <hi>Dulia</hi> onely, but alſo <hi>Hiperdulia,</hi> a more eſpeciall ſeruice, euen ſo forre foorth as to bend both the knees, yea to bow with the belly to the earth, euen to inuocate it as liuing, &amp;c. But what aunſwere doth S. <hi>Cirill</hi> make him?<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et paucis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriectis.</hi> Abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que labore demonſtrabimus eluſmodi ſermones à malis cogitationibus profectos, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremam ſapere imperitiam.</note> 
                  <hi>But</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>we can eaſily proue that theſe ſpeeches proceed of bad thoughts, and relye vpon extreame ignoraunce.</hi> And wherein? Sauing in that hee did imagine that becauſe they painted the Croſſe, they did it to worſhip it? And therefore euen at once he bringeth him backe from the Crucifixe to the crucified: from the ſigne to the thing ſignified: from the pretended oderation of the wood, to the miſtery of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9932:22"/>our redemption,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Nam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, qua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> omnibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> aequalia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unitatis ſolio conſidere, non capinam tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> arbitratus eſt ſe eſſe aequalem Deo, ſed ſerp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, formam ſerui accipiens, contemtaque ignominia cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſuſtinuit vt corruptionis abolueret po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam: Vnus pro omnibus moriuus, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatur vt à mortis laqueis humanum eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peretgenus. &amp;c Vt ſpirituales ſaceret adoratores, mortuumque faciens in nobis ſenſum carnis, filios eſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret Dei eos qui in ſe crediderunt, &amp;c.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Our Lord and Sauiour</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>might doe equally with the Father, hee might ſit vpon the Throne of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and yet neuer be imputed vnto him for theft, in that he made him elfe equall with him: but hee humbled himſelfe; hee tooke vpon him the ſhape of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; hee contemned ignominy that hee might beare the Croſſe, to take away corruption, and alone for all men to dye &amp; riſe againe, to deliuer mankinde out of the ſhares of death. &amp;c. To procure to himſelfe worſhippers in Spirit.</hi> Note, <hi>in Spirit, and not worſhippers of flockes and ſtones; to the end to make vs the children of God, by killing the motions of the fleſh in vs, &amp;c.</hi> And as concerning this wood, he ſayth.<note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Et paulo poſt.</hi> Haec omnia recordari nos facit ſalutare lignum; &amp; ſuadet vt cogitemus quod ſicut dicit diuinus Paulus vnus pro omnibus mortuus eſt, vt viuentes non vltra ſibi ipſis viuant, ſed ei qui pro ipſis mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt, &amp; reſurrexit.</note> 
                  <hi>This healthfull wood putteth vs in minde of all theſe thinges, and exhorteth vs to remember the ſaying of S.</hi> Paul. <hi>One only dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all, to the end that liuing they ſhould not heereafter liue to themſelues, but to him that dyed and roſe againe for them.</hi> Againe,<note n="e" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Et pa. ſeq</hi> 135. Vis igitur, vir ſtrenus, vt lignum quod nos ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordationem omnis virtutis inducit abiiciamus &amp; relinquamus pueriſque &amp; mulier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis tua proponamus</note> 
                  <hi>Wouldſt thou</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wiſh vs to reiect this wood, that putteth vs in minde of all goodnes? and to ſet before our wiues and children thy paintings.</hi> Namely, as hee did a little before diſcourſe, the patrons of all vncleaneneſſe and polution? Of the worſhipping therefore, or adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this wood (albeit this was the very fit place) not one word. And indeed ſaith the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> why ſhould it ſeeme more ſtrange in <hi>Cirill</hi> then in <hi>Minutius Felix,</hi> who doth expreſſely ſay;<note n="f" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Minus Felix in Octauto, pa.</hi> 20. <hi>edi. Heidenberg. Lud. Lucii.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cis nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>oramus, nec optamus.</note> 
                  <hi>We doe neither worſhip nor wiſh
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9932:22"/>the Croſse.</hi> Then in S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who ſpeaking of <hi>Helen</hi> the mother of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> ſaith.<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vtique, quia lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eti error &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> impio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> Hellen <hi>worſhipped <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the wood for that had been an error and heat burniſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Where the queſtion concerned not the Croſſe onely, but the true Croſſe. Heereto the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> replyed, that theſe places were to be vnderſtood by the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Dulium</hi> and <hi>Latria.</hi> The L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> old vphold that this diſtinction was friuolous, vnknowne in the holy Scriptures, or Fathers; impoſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. <hi>Anguſtive</hi> who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnderſtood it. But he ere into would the Lord of <hi>Eur.</hi> neuer enter. Laſtly, that this great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (for he took pleaſure in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,) who had been a Chriſtian, and was acquainted with the Chriſtian mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, would neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> puted it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it not been liue. But let the L. of <hi>Eu.</hi> marke, what preiud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e he hath here wrought to the ſacriſice of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, before he was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e. And euen there where <hi>Julian</hi> obiecteth to the Chriſtians, that they ſacrificed not; ſaying vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyrill Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. lib.</hi> 9. Vos antem inuento nouo ſacrificio non vltra indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, quare non ſacrificatis</note> 
                  <hi>And you my maſters that haue no more to do will</hi> Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>why doyou not ſacrifice, in finding out ſome new ſacrifice?</hi> He wil beare vs witnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chriſtians in thoſe daies did not ſacrifice; that in hewe of the Iewiſh ſacrifices, which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had giuen ouer, they had not as yet brought in any new ſacrifice: Euen he, let vs ſay with the L. of <hi>Eu.</hi> who ſhould not haue forgotten the ordinary ſacrifice of the Sonne of God, dayly reiterated by the Prieſtes, had it been at that time in vſe in the Church. Heere the King himſelfe perceiuing that they could pretend no vntruth againſt this place, pronounced aloude that both ſides had reaſon. And therupon the L. Chauncellor pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſimply; <hi>That the words are not to be found in S.</hi> Cirill. So leauing matter ſufficient to inferre, that the ſence was neuerheleſſe to be gathered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:9932:23"/>
               <head>The ſeauenth place out of <hi>Peter Crinitus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THen they came to the ſeauenth place out of <hi>Peter Crinitus</hi> that the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> and his ſide had made ſo much adoe of,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char c. 3. edit. 1. p. 223. l. 10. edit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 239. l. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. edit. 3. p. 199. l. 29.</note> taken out of the 223. pag. lin 10. Where the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> alleaging this <hi>Crinitus, de honeſta diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina, lib.</hi> 9. in the Margent for his author, ſaith; That the Emperors <hi>Theodoſius</hi> &amp; <hi>Valens</hi> had made an edict in theſe words.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fet. Crinitus. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. de honeſta diſcipl. cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Lugd. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt. Gryphiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> 1543. Cum ſit nobis cura di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s in rebus o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nibus ſuperni numinis religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem tue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ſig num Saluato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Chriſti ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini quidem concedimas coloribus, lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, aliaue mate ria ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ingere, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculpere, aut pingere. Sed quodeumque reperitur tolli iubemus; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſſima poena eos multando. qui contrariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deceretis noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris &amp; impetio qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>equain ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarint.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe our greateſt care concerneth the ſeruice of God, we forbid all perſons that they ſhall not make the ſigne of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, neyther in colour, in mettall, or in any other matter; that they ſhall not graue, paint or carue it: but wee will whereſoeuer it may be found, that it be taken away, vnder paine that all offenders to the contrary, ſhal be moſt grieuouſly puniſhed.</hi> Heere againſt the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> pretended falſehood, becauſe (ſaid he) this law was otherwiſe ſet downe in the Code; namely, that it is prohibited to paint or carue the Croſſe vpon the earth, <hi>humt,</hi> in which word conſiſteth the force of this law. The L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> anſwereth; There can be no falſification, becauſe in <hi>Crinitus</hi> whom he hath alleaged it is ſo ſet downe; that <hi>Crinitus</hi> ſayth that he tooke it <hi>(ex libris Auguſtalibus)</hi> out of the Imperiall bookes, others peraduenture then the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort: &amp; it may be himſelf hath read ſundry ſorts of the common ſort. That he cited <hi>Valens</hi> and <hi>Theo loſius,</hi> who rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned not together, and ſo hee might confound their edictes into one: That theſe wordes in <hi>Crinitus. Nemini concedemus coloribus, lapide, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e materia ſingere, inſculpere, aut pingere,</hi> can no way bee entred into the place of theſe of the Code.<note n="b" place="margin">li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. c. nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni lic. ſig. ſalu. &amp;c.</note> Lib. 1. tit. 7. leg. 1. where we read, <hi>Nemins licere vel in ſolo, vel in ſilice, velta marmoribus humi poſitis inſculpere, vel pingere:</hi> too far from the letters or ſillables, alſo from the text, to bee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9932:23"/>eyther ingengred or corrupted the one by the other. Contrariwiſe, that it was more likely that as ſuperſtition encreaſed in the Church in the dayes of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> that <hi>Tribonian</hi> accommodated that law of <hi>Valens</hi> and <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> to his time, by adding <hi>humi:</hi> Which the learned <hi>Cuiatius,</hi> and after him, all other lawyers had noted in ſundry lawes, as well of the common wealth as of the Empyre. Whereof likewiſe we haue one teſtimony in matter of the Croſſe: for the puniſhment by the Croſſe being by all Chriſtian Emperours forbidden, in euery place where the Romaine lawes had <hi>Crucem, Tribonian</hi> put in <hi>Furcam.</hi> Infinite other like examples might wee alleadge. Beſides there was no cauſe that this law ſhould ſeeme more ſtrange then the 36. Canon of the Eliber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin counſell.<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil Eliber. c.</hi> 36. Placuir picturas in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiis eſſe non debere, ne quod adoratur in parietibus depingatur.</note> 
                  <hi>Jt hath pleaſed, or it hath been thought good, that there ſhould be no painting in the Churches, to the ende that which is worſhipped, ſhould not be painted on the walles.</hi> For (ſayth the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi>) if the Croſſe or Crucifixe were worſhipped, they were not then painted in the churches: if they were painted, they were not then worſhipped. To this latter reaſon the L. of <hi>Eureux</hi> did reply, that this Canon was otherwiſe to bee vnderſtood; namely, that they ſhould not be paynted vpon the walles, but vpon looſe tables that might be faſtned to the walles. Alſo that that was theyr manner ſtill in the Dioceſſe of <hi>Eliberis</hi> in Spaine. But heereof let the reader iudge by theſe words, <hi>Picturas in Eccleſiis eſſe non debere,</hi> for the queſtion is, that there ſhould bee no paintinges in the Church, eyther painted or faſtned. And ſo did the Elders vnderſtand it. As alſo our <hi>Agobard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> who writ ſince the yeare 800.<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Agobardus Epiſc. Lugdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis contra e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem qui pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis &amp; imag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inibus ſanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adorationis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. Qui liber manuſcr. extat in Biblioth. S. Victoris.</hi> Si vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derimus pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natos Angelos pictos, praedica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Apoſtolos. martyres tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, nullum ab imaginibus, quas aſpicimus, auxiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſperate debemus, quia nec bene, nec malè poſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t facere. Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te nimiru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adeiuſmodi euacuanda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperſtitione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab Orthodoxis Patribus definitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, Picturas in Eccleſia fieri non debere, ne quod colitur &amp; adoratur in parietibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingatur.</note> 
                  <hi>Albeit wee ſee the Angels painted with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9932:24"/>their winges, the Apoſtles preaching, the Martirs ſuffering their torments, yet are wee not to hop, for any ſuccour from the Jmages that we ſee, for they can doe neither good nor euill. And therefore to roote out this ſuperſtition, the Orthodorall Fathers haue very well decreed, that there ſhould bee no pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in the Church: that that which is ſerued and worſhipped ſhould not be printed vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Alleaging the words of this Counſell. All which notwithſtanding the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> grew out of patience, that this place that hee had made ſo great account of, was not condemned of falſehoode: And therefore moſt importunately both with hand and voice vrgod the Commiſſioners. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the L. Chauncellor procounced, <hi>That indeed the L. of</hi> Pleſſis <hi>had truely quoted the place of</hi> Crinitus, <hi>but that</hi> Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus <hi>was deceiued.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The eight place out of <hi>S. Bernard.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THen followeth a place of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 3. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. ch. 15. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. 1. p. 60 p. l. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. p. 648. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. edit. 3. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.</note> taken out of his 174. Epiſtle to the Canons of <hi>Lyons,</hi> alleaged by the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> pa. 604. li. 9. (for thus they leapt from one to another) where he entreeteth of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> Out of this Epiſtle againſt the falſe honours attributed to the holy Virgin, be took theſe words. <hi>She need no falſe honours, being as ſhe is, at the fith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s thereof: It is no honour, but a taking away of her honour. The feaſt of her conception was neuer well inſtituted.</hi> Which propoſitions the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> gathered out of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places of this Epiſtle. And the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> pretende. falſehood againſt this place: becauſe (ſaid he) the Lord of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> had omitted that which came betweene the two clauſes. <hi>Magnifica gratiae inuentricem, mediatricem ſalutis,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9932:24"/>reſtauratricem ſaeculorum. Magnifie the inuentrix of grace, the mediatrixe of ſaluation, the reſtoratrixe of the world, &amp;c.</hi> The Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> vpholdeth that in this allegation, he vſeth neyther mayming nor fraude: No fraude, for he doth not diſſemble the commendations that S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> attributeth to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> where. ſoone after he ſayth; <hi>That in other places S.</hi> Bernard <hi>helpeth to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce the ſame abuſe, where he ſaith. O man, thou haſt a ſure acceſſe to God, where the Mother is before the Sonne, the Sonne before the Father, the Mother ſhewing her Sonne her boſome and breſtes; the Sonne ſhewing the Father his ſide and his woundes.</hi> What could be ſpoken more ſincerely? and dooth not this import more aduantage, then the words that the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> tooke holde of? <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diavicem ſalutis, the mediatrixe of ſaluation,</hi> which cannot be borne, but ſo ſarre forth as the Virgin was the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſaluation; Neither truely any mayming, for the clauſes are diſtinguiſhed by great letters; and which is more the ſame that concerneth the feaſt of the concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is repented in ſundry places, both before and after the ſame, whereby the allegation dooth beginne. <hi>Shee need no falſe honours, &amp;c.</hi> Neyther hath the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> heerein hurt any but himſelfe, in that labouring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> after breuity he ſayd not enough. baint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth to the Chanons of <hi>Lyons.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard. epiſt</hi> 174. <hi>edit. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſionſ. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1566. Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ſaris quid viſum ſucrit hoc te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pore quibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum voluiſſe mutare colore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> optimum, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam inducendo celebritatem, quam ritus Eccleſiae neſeit, non probat rario, non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendarantiqua traditio. Numquid Patribus doctiores aut deuotiores ſumus? Pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſe praeſumimus quicquid ipſorum in talibus prudentia praeteriuet. Nec ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d tale eſt quod niſi praetereundum ſucrit, Partum quiuerit omnino diligentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praeteriiſic. At val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de honoranda es, inquis, mater Domini. Bene admones, ſed honor Reginae iudicium deligit. Virgo regia falſo non eget honore, veris cumulata honorum titulis, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>We doe ſurely maruatle what toy hath taken ſome of you in the heades to alter your good colour, by bringing in (note for the conception) a new feaſt which the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Church know not, which reaſon alloweth not,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9932:25"/>which auncient tradition doth not recommend. Are we ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better learned, or more deuout then the Fathers? Shall wee preſume or dare to vndertake with perrill, all that in ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters their diſcretion hath omitted? Neyther is this matter of ſo ſmall importaunce, that their dilligence would in any wiſe haue omitted it, if it had not been to be omitted: But thou wilt ſay, the Mother of our Lord muſt bee honoured. Thou giueſt vs good warning, but the honour of the Queene muſt bee done vnto her with iudgement. The royall Virgin</hi> (note for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete honours) <hi>needed no falſe honours, being as ſhe is, laden with the true tytles of honour.</hi> Wherein wee are then to note the true periods cyted by the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis,</hi> euen that which concerneth the conception, and the other that toucheth the falſe honours attributed to the holie Virgin, immediately and in one ſequence, whereby hee was not bound to adde that which followed farre en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough off, <hi>Magnifica gratiae inuentricem, &amp;c.</hi> For had hee vndertaken to ſet downe the whole Epiſtle, hee proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth the reaſons, in regard wherof the feaſt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception hath no reaſon, in a long diſcourſe, and toward the concluſion redoubleth the ſame ſentences, that hee had ſet at the beginning in his preface;<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibidem, ſub ſinem pag.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co glorioſam de Spiritu S. concepiſſe, non autem &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptam fuiſſe: dico peperiſſe virginem, non tamen &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam a virgine. Alioquin vbi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit praerogatiua matris Domini &amp;c. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt hoc virginem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norare, ſed honori detrahere &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſay</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that the glorious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin conceiued of the holy Ghoſt, but not that ſhe was conceiued: That ſhe a Virgin brought foorth a childe, not that ſhee was childed of a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin. Otherwiſe what prerogatiue were it to the Mother of the Lord? &amp;c. This is no honouring of the Virgin, but rather an abaſement of her honour, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore ſayth he:<note n="c" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Et paulò poſt.</hi> Cum haec ita ſe habeant, quaenam iam erit feſtiuae ratio conceptionis? quo pacto, inquam aut ſanctus aſſeretur concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, qui de Spiritu S. no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, ne dicam de peccato eſt: aut feſtus habebitur qui minime ſanctus eſt? Libentur glorioſa hoc honore carebit, quo vel peccatum honorari, vel fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa induci videtur ſanctitas. Alioquin, nulla ei ratione placebit contra Eccleſiae ritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumata nouitas mater temeritatis ſoror ſuperſtitionis, filia leuitatis.</note> 
                  <hi>Things being at this
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9932:25"/>paſſe, what reaſon can there be to celebrate the conception? J ſay, how can we affirme the conception to be holy, which is not of the holy Ghoſt, J will not ſay which is of ſinne? Or howe ſhall we ſanctifie this conception which cannot bee holy? Surely the holy Virgin can be content to forbeare this honour, whereby her ſinne ſhall be honoured, or a falſe holines brought in.</hi> In another place; <hi>No noueltie preſumed without reaſon, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the cuſtome of the Church, can ſhe like of, Mother of rashneſſe, Siſter of ſuperſtition, Daughter of inconſtancie or lightneſſe.</hi> Then dooth he afterward referre himſelfe to the deciſion of the Church of Rome, which belonged not to our purpoſe. Nowe let any vpright minde iudge, whether there were any holde to bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt this place, whereupon notwithſtanding for the ſatisfying of his importunity it was pronounced; <hi>That it had beene good to diſtinguiſh the two places of S.</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard <hi>in one ſelfe booke (namely of this ſelfe Epiſtle) by one, &amp;c.</hi> Which neuertheleſſe albeit repeated in two ſeueral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, doe immediatly follow each other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ninth place out of <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ninth was taken out of <hi>Theodoret</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 113 Pſalme, alleaged by the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> pag. 218. lyn. 9. in theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Lib. 2. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. ch. 2. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. 1. p. 218. l. 9. edit. 2. p. 234. l. 21. edit. 3. p. 195 l. 13</note> 
                  <hi>God</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>dooth what he pleaſeth, but Images are made as it pleaſeth men: they haue the habitation of the ſences, but ſences they haue none: being heerein inferiour to the flyes, fleaſe, and all vermine: and it is meete that they that worſhip them should looſe both reaſon and ſence.</hi> And the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> had taken the moſt ſubſtantiall clauſes of this Pſalme. But the Lord of <hi>Eur.</hi> pretended falſehood in two reſpectes: In the tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9932:26"/>becauſe he expreſſed <hi>Simulacra</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by <hi>Images:</hi> for hee would haue it <hi>Ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> In omiſſion, becauſe he had not ſet downe <hi>a Gentibus cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, worſhipped or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ued by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s:</hi> to diſtinguiſh them (ſayd hee) from the Images of the Chriſtians. To the firſt the Lord of <hi>Pliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is</hi> anſwered that theſe wordes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Simulach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, Imagines</hi> did vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe for one. And this did the Lord of <hi>Pliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is</hi> offer him to prooue; but he would not enter thereinto. And indeed in the 40. of <hi>Eſay</hi> where the olde interpreter ſayth, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulacrum</hi> the Septuaginte ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Image. And in the 4. of <hi>Deutronomy,</hi> the olde interpreter tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſlateth the woord <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Imaginem,</hi> the Septuaginte <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That the ſame olde interpreter tranſlateth in the 33 of the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles Simulacrum</hi> that which the Septuaginte <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And the firſt of the <hi>Romaines</hi> where S. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Lombard, Caietan, Stapuienſis, Oſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue tranſlated <hi>Simulacrum.</hi> In the Scriptures they are therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different. For the Fathers,<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iuſt. Martyr in Tryphone. pag.</hi> 251 <hi>edit. Hierca. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel. Grae. Lat.</hi> Qut per Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſanxit <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ne qua omnino ſieret vel imago, vel ſimditudo, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que coru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae in coelo ſunt. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtm Martir</hi> layth, <hi>That God forbad Moſes to make any Image or ſimilitude:</hi> where the Septuaginte ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee ſayth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertullianus de Idolelatria ch.</hi> 3. <hi>Ex edit. Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>chi.</hi> Ad hoc neceſſaria eſt vocabuſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tio; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Graece f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m ſonat; ab eo per diminutionem <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> deductum, aeque apud nos formu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Igitur omnis forma vel ſormulo, Idolu ſe dici expoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it, inde Idololatria om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis circa omne Idolum ſamulatus &amp; ſeruius.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian; E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s, in Greeke, ſignifieth forme or figure; whereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the diminutiue</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>which we doe interpret a ſmall forme or figure; therefore euery forme or ſmall ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne muſt bee called</hi> Idolum. <hi>And thereof Idolatrie, all honour and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that is done, circa omne Idolum, to any forme or figure.</hi> Againe,<note n="c" place="bottom">
                     <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cap.</hi> 4. Qui ſeruitis lapid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus, &amp; qui i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>agines ſacitis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>cas &amp; arge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eas, &amp; ligneas &amp; lapideas.</note> 
                  <hi>You that ſerue the ſtones, and that make Jmages of golde, and of ſiluer, and of wood, and of ſtone, &amp;c.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſpeaking of the Gentils;<note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Item</hi> Eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, imagia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratio Idololatria.</note> 
                  <hi>Their Images are Jdols, the conſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratioon of Images is Jdolatry. Minu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius Fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9932:26"/>vpon the reproach of the Heathen <hi>Celſus,</hi> caſt in his diſh, that the Chriſtians had no Images.<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix pag</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Heidelberg</hi> Quis dubitat hotum imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ratas vulgus orare &amp; publice colere.</note> 
                  <hi>Who doubteth</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>but the Heathen direct their prayers to the Images, that theſe men haue conſecrated, as alſo that they honour them pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely with religious ſeruice?</hi> and within three lynes after, he calleth them notwithſtanding <hi>Simulachra;</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mox.</hi> Quod ſi in animum quis inducat tormentis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; quibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> machinis ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne formetur, erubeſcet &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>If a man ſhould imagine with what tooles euery Image is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore alſo it commeth that <hi>Jſidore</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no other ſubtilty;<note n="g" place="margin">Iſider. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> li. <hi>8.</hi> ca. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Simulacra</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>a ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine nuncupata, eo quòd manu artificis ex lapide, aliàue materia eorum vultus imitantur, in quorum honorem firguntur; Jma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſo called in regard of the ſimilitude, becauſe by the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hand, whether of ſtene or other ſubſtance, they imitate the countenaunces of thoſe to whoſe honour they are fayned.</hi> Euen among the Schoole-men, <hi>Thomas</hi> calleth that<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Thomas in</hi> 1. <hi>ad Corinth. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>lect.</hi> 1 Simulacrum quod ad ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudine alicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius rei natrua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis fit.</note> 
                  <hi>Jmage, that is made to the reſemblaunce of any natural thing.</hi> Alſo <hi>Durand,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Durand. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mario, art.</hi> 4. Idolorum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modicus vſus reprobatur, modicus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur.</note> 
                  <hi>The immoderate vſe of Jdols is reprooued, the moderate approoued,</hi> 1 of Images. And in the ſame Chap. <hi>Nonſacies Idolum, thou ſhalt not make thee any Idoll.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Simulachra Gentium Argentum &amp; Aurum, the Jmages of the Gentils are ſiluer and golde, &amp;c. By ſuch authorities</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the exceſſiue and immoderate vſe of Images is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, &amp;c.</hi> Holcor <hi>likewiſe expounded a place of the booke of Wiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome,</hi> Chap. 3. againſt the Idolaters;<hi rend="sup">l</hi> 
                  <hi>In this part doth the holy Ghoſt beginne to condemne Jdolaters, and thoſe that doe honour and ſerue Images and artificiall figures.</hi> Againe,<note n="m" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ibid Exodi</hi> 2 <hi>dicitur.</hi> No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facies tibi Imaginem, neque vllam ſimilitudinem.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not make thee any Image, &amp;c.</hi> tranſlating <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for <hi>Image.</hi> So new a matter is this diſtinction betweene Idoll and Image among the Chriſtians;<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c:</hi> 3 Ex his &amp; ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus auctoritatibus reprobatur nimius imaginum vſus. <hi>Holcot in lib. Sapien. lect.</hi> 157. <hi>in verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. In hac parte Spiritus S. conſequenter aggreditur repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare Idololatras qui colunt Imagines &amp; artificiales figuras.</note> yea
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9932:27"/>euen ſo farre foorth that Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth, expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ten commaundements, confoundeth them in theſe words;<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pius Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ca. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>pto</hi> 2. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cripturis iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra &amp; imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ictas le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>us, Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, ſerp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ei.</note> 
                  <hi>Jn the Scriptures we d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eread that by Gods commaundement they made Images and likeneſſes, as of the Cherubins. of the ſerpent &amp;c.</hi> Now againſt theſe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, which the Lord of <hi>Pleſsis</hi> would haue alleaged to the Lord of <hi>Eur.</hi> he appealed for help to <hi>Henry Stephens Theſaurus</hi> (he ſhuld haue ioyned with it the Card. of <hi>Sens,</hi> his <hi>Calepine</hi>) where againſt they might with more reaſon haue oppoſed the olde Gloſſer: <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Lakenes, Jmage, Jdoll, Picture,</hi> where all theſe wordes are confounded together. Thus much for the falſehood committed in the tranſlation. Now for the ſecond, in the omiſſion of theſe words, <hi>a Gentibus cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, worſhipped or ſerued by the Gentils;</hi> The L. of <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that of themſelues they did ſufficiently ſupply, in that the Pſalme ſpake directly againſt the Images or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols of the Gentils; conſidering alſo that in thoſe dayes the Chriſtians had no Images, as is already ſufficiently prooued: which notwithſtanding was no let, but that that Pſalme and text might at theſe dayes be applyable againſt the Images of the Chriſtians, euen as wel as they were or might haue been in the olde Teſtament againſt Images of the Iewes, when after the imitation of the Heathen, they diuerted to Idolatry. As indeed the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments did equally concurre each with other; that they were made, but not made; that they receiued honour of their colour &amp; mettal, &amp; ſhape from the hand &amp; pleſure of the painter; that they had the ſeates of the ſences, but were inſencible, &amp;c. Hereto the L. of <hi>Eu.</hi> replyed that the deuils or <hi>demons</hi> inhabited in the Idols of the Heathen; which was graunted him in regard of ſome, but few, and denyed in the moſt part and ordinary. The L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine replyed, that in thoſe dayes, and before the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9932:27"/>had Images: witneſſe (ſaith hee) <hi>Theodoret</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is &amp; porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus ei paruas poſuerint ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, hine ſibi praeſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ium &amp; tutela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Cum ergo venirent innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merabiles; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabantur aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, &amp; expelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceis illis veſtibꝰ aliquam preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem; primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quidem abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum &amp; alienu exiſtimans ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſignem ſibi haberie hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, deinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam rem ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre ferens vt nimis laborio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus eſt illa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in columna ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem: primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iubens aedificari ſex cubitorum, deinde duodecim poſtea autem: vigin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iduorum, &amp;c.</note> who in the hiſtory of Saintes, telleth vs that <hi>Simon</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Stilites,</hi> was ſo famous in <hi>Rome,</hi> that in the porches of all their ſhops they had ſet him vpſmal Images, hoping for ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their hands; And this did the aſſiſtants receiue with great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe. Heere let the reader note that the Author ſaith <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en ſay:</hi> Alſo, <hi>in the porches of their ſhops,</hi> not in the Churches. Againe, <hi>Poſuerunt, they planted the common people,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the Church: But which is more, that theſe honors thus done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him did ſo grieue him, that hee det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmined to cauſe the piller to be built, vpon the top whereof he purpoſed to ende his life, that ſo he might ſequeſter himſelfe from the world. Finally the L. Chauncellor pronounced, <hi>That this place could not be vnderſtood but of the Jdols of the Gentils, and not of the J<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the Chriſtians, as appeared in theſe words; a Gentibus culta; &amp; quae in Gentibus adorantur, that had bin omitted.</hi> But in conſcience of a Diuine, is this any let why by Anology the ſame may not be alleaged againſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Images of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians?</p>
               <p>Thus were theſe nine places examined, and no more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it grew late: where may bee eaſily diſcerned that the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> who had ſtrained him in the arguing of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, finding that he was diſgraced by thy Kings preſence, whoſe religion, albeit not directly, he did impugne; &amp; gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the applauſe that ſeconded all his his aduerſaryes ſayings, withall ſeeing that they permitted not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners time enough to read and conſider of the places; and euidently perceiuing by all the countenaunces and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that this action was prepared (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whatſoeuer he could doe) to his diſaduantage, did to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ende ſeeme to ſertle to yeelde more force to this conteſtation; Vnprofitably indeede imployed, in that it had been in vaine more earneſtly to defend the truth, already condemned vpon the file. Yet was he prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for it, and had watched very late oue: night (albeit hee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9932:28"/>had loſt the night before) to continue the next morning, had not God in the night time ſent him a great weakeneſſe of the ſtomacke, with extraordinary vomits, not without a Feuer.</p>
               <p>Vpon which accident, the Lord of <hi>Riuier,</hi> the Kinges chiefe Phiſition counſailed him to haue ſpeedy recourſe to ſome remedyes. And therefore the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> moſt humbly beſought his Maieſty to holde him excuſed during this ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Whereupon the next day the Preſidents of <hi>Thou, Pythou, Caſaubon,</hi> and <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tin,</hi> were lycenſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</p>
               <p>Heere let all ſuch as haue ſeene the Lord of <hi>Eureux</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or heard him ſpeake in company, remember whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee hath produced any thing anſwerable eyther to theyr conceipt, or to his owne ſpeeches, to their hope, or to his promiſes. For where are theſe heynous, litterall, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culary falſehoods and vntruthes, which might bee diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the firſt opening of the bookes, and found at the firſt ſight?</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, which one place is there amongſt them all, where they were not driuen to enter very farre into the ſence of the text; and right, before they could aſſeſſe iudgement? Yet in the meane time vppon theſe great wordes who was not purpoſed to ſee the Authors falſely alleaged, the ſuppoſed places, ſet downe vpon plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to deceiue the people? Yet who can doubt but that theſe ſixty places by him preſented, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe force was to bee perceaued in theſe nyne, are the chiefeſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee expected greateſt ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auntage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith bee placed them in the fore fronte of his battle, and in them cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from among 5000. or more, with ſo great leaſure and labour both of himſelfe and others, he had repoſed his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended victory?</p>
               <p>Now to come without paſſion to the very matter, what hath he gotten, or rather what hath hee not loſt with all
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9932:28"/>ſound iudgementes in the examination of theſe places? For what one falſehood is there eyther judged, or to be iudged among theſe nyne? Or may in ſome one of them, the omiſſion of ſome word, for the moſt part indifferent with men of iudgement, bee of any force againſt the Author, the booke, or any part of the booke? Yet let vs yeild them what they can aske in theſe places, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of notwithſtanding our ſelues without contradiction doe retayne the beſt and chiefe part;) theſe places picked out heere and there, and in euery place, can they relieue Tranſubſtantiation, the inuocation of Saynts, the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, ouerthrowen throughout the courſe of the whole booke by the authoritye of the Scriptures, the practiſe of the Primatiue Church, and the conſent of the moſt notable Fathers? <hi>Scot, Durand</hi> and ſuch like, who are not alleaged, according to the phraſe of the Pallace, but <hi>cumulatiuè,</hi> as it were to make vp mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: which croſſed out, would bee no weakening to the booke: or kept, make it not the ſtronger: theſe are they from whome they hoped, for the rayſing againe of their Maſſe, for the proofe of Tranſubſtantiation in the Maſſe, notwithſtanding argued, beaten and ouerthrowen by themſelues, if they durſt haue ſtood to it. And the like let vs ſay of the moſt part of the reſt. Who therefore cannot ſee that where hee ſeeketh to make moſt beſt of his force, he hath made moſt demonſtration of his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? where hee looked to haue bleamiſhed the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritye of his aduerſaty, hee hath cauſed it to breake foorth and to ſhine more cleare and bright. Surely (for wee may ſay it truely) there was neuer Booke eyther in our age or in the formerages (no not the quoyne in the generall eſſayes) examined ſo ſeuerely or putto ſo ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous tryall. And yet when they that haue been made drunke with this ſmoke ſhall growe ſober agayne, when they ſhall bee diſpoſed earneſtly to conſider what
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9932:29"/>they haue ſeene, what they haue done, that the deep wounds which this pretended <hi>Goliab</hi> promiſed, are leſſe then ſmall ſcratches: his blowes with his club leſſe then phillips; what ſhall they catch, vnleſſe by the affected reprehenſion of fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous matters, they tooke ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edfaſt aſſurance of the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth of the principals, of the moſt firme, of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt? To ſpeake Lawyer-like; what can they iudge but that theſe ſlight exceptions haue ſtrengthned the rule? as a great man of our age ſayd very well. It is no good proofe of a matter, that there is nothing to be repugned: but rather an argument to the contrary, that it hath been but ſuperficial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looked into: but that is wel tryed wherin they reprooue what they may, and finde but little to be reprooued. Were we to examine with like authority and rigour, not the books of their perticuler Doctors, but euen their Cannon law, theyr decree it ſelfe confirmed, Canonized and verified by the Popes; what one diſtinction ſhall eſcape notable falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, both in number and without number? wherein wee ſhall not finde the places both of the Fathers &amp; counſailes, curtalled of their moſt eſſentiall words; falſified, ſuppoſed, compoſed vpon pleaſure, to fit them to the profit, authority or doctrine of the Popes? For to ſet downe ſome example, leauing the Donation of <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> the oath <hi>Ego Ludouicus</hi> with many others diſavowed by the learned. In the 3. famous Counſaile at <hi>Carthage</hi> where S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was in perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the 31. Canon, ſpeaketh directly againſt the vſurpings &amp; enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes of the Church of Rome.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ag.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imiliter pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ut vt preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eri &amp; diaconi &amp; reliqui infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiores clerici, in tis, quas ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, cauſis, ſi de propriorum Epiſcoporum iudiciis quera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vicini Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>opi cos audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Ne appellent ad iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod eſt extra mare, ſed ad prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſuaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inciarum, quemadmodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; de Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e de ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Qui au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ad trans marina iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia prouocant, a nullo in Af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an ad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munionem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Prieſts ſhall not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to any iudgement beyond the Seas, but to the Primates of their owne prouince, as the Biſhops haue often defined: likewiſe that ſuch as ſhould appeale to any iudgement boyond the Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſhould not by any bee receiued into the Communion in Affricke.</hi> This Cannon employed in the<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Decretall 2. q. 6. <hi>Placuit vt presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eri,</hi> with what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience could they adde theſe words. <hi>Niſi fortè Romanam ſedem appellauerint, vnleſſe per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>duenture they appeale to the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of Rome,</hi> which viterly ouerthroweth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9932:29"/>the meaning of the Counſell? In the 73. Canon it was ſaid;<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. ciu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. c.</hi> 73. Placuit vt Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri, Epiſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi &amp; Diaconi propriis termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis etiam a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xoribus: quod niſi fecerint Eccleſiaſtico ordine moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur.</note> 
                  <hi>It hath ſeemed good that the Prieſtes, Biſhops &amp; Deacons in their proper turnes ſhould abſtaine euen from theyr wiues.</hi> Wherein it appeareth that they were maried, &amp; notwithſtanding theyr orders, kept their wiues, but as their courſe came about to ſerue, they did abſtaine, according likewiſe to the Canon of the ſixt Counſaile: With what credite haue they inſerted it into the decrees?<note n="d" place="margin">C. Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>t. diſt. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>d.</hi> 32. Cha. <hi>Placuit,</hi> cutting of theſe wordes, <hi>Propriis terminis, in their proper turnes,</hi> in the courſe of their ſeruice, which make the whole ſence to bring in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inſteed of marriage. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> likewiſe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which were Canonicall Scriptures, whereupon euery Chriſtians faith ſhould depend: ſayd,<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. de. doctr. Chriſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. In Canonicis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n: Scripturis, Eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arum Catholicatum quamplurium ſequatur auct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quas ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. illae ſunt, quae Apoſtolica <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bere &amp; Epiſtolas ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt. Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitigitur hune modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, vt eas quae ab omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus accipian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Eccleſiis Catholicis, praeponat eis quas quaedam non accipiunt, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>In the Canon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cal Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Churches, let them follow the authoritie of the moſt part, among the which</hi> (namely Churches) <hi>thoſe indeed are, which haue deſerued eyther to be the Seas of the Apoſtles, or to receiue Epiſtles,</hi> (as Rome, Epheſus, Corinthus, Theſſolonica, &amp;c.) <hi>to preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r thoſe that all the Catholike Churches do receiue, before ſuch as ſome doe not receuie, &amp;c.</hi> With what ſhameleſſenes could they cyte this place in theſe wordes.<note n="f" place="bottom">
                     <hi>In Canonicis. diſt.</hi> 19 Inter quas fane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llae ſint quas Apoſlolica ſedes habere &amp; ab ea alii meruerunt acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re Epiſtolas, &amp;c.</note> Among which indeed let thoſe be which the Apoſtolike Sea hath deſerued to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and which the other Churches haue deſerued or had the fauour to receiue from her: So to make S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who neuer thought of it, to Canonize the Decretals of all the Popes: and that, euen by quoting this Cannon by name out of S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> 2. booke <hi>de Doctrina Chriſtiana.</hi> To bee ſhort,<note n="g" place="bottom">
                     <hi>In ſummario ſupradicti Canonis ciuſd. diſt.</hi> 19. Inter Canonicas Scripturas Decretales Epiſtolae connumerantur.</note> 
                  <hi>The Decretall Epiſtles are accounted among the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll Scriptures,</hi> falſehoodes indeed, truely litteral, &amp; indeed deſtroyers of the ſence, ſuch indeed as the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> did promiſe, not ſuch as he did produce. And of this quote only in the decree we may ſhew them whole hundreds, whole Chiliade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; (to ſtand vpon the very termes of the Lord of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9932:30"/>
                  <hi>Eureux</hi>) of perſect tale without amplification. The like may we ſay of the Maſter of the ſentences, whome the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue taken for theyr text of all their commentaries, for the argument of all their ſtudies; at euery fields length cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the places of the Fathers, to accommodate them to the doctrine of his time. And in three leaues that the L. of <hi>Eu.</hi> hath put to printing in all his life (how may it then bee in theſe great volumes?) hee cannot ſcape free from the like cryme.</p>
               <p>Thus haue you heard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true proceedings &amp; hiſtory of this Conference, which I was forced to ſet downe becauſe the people were brought into a wrong immagination, vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the coppy of a certaine letter that was printed and publiſhed all about, read in the Pulpits, and diſtributed through all the parriſhes in the Realme: euen ſo farre foorth that the L. of <hi>Pleſ.</hi> comming to <hi>Saumur,</hi> found there aboue 100. Coppies, part printed at <hi>Teurs,</hi> part coppyed by the commaundement of ſome of the bench, by all the notaryes in the towne, whereby the inhabitantes began to murmure one againſt another. It is therefore but a ſinall matter to let the L. of <hi>Eur.</hi> flye paſſe for an Elephant, and an illuſion that ſhall goe: Truth will ouercome in a ſhort time. But let his Maieſty in diſcretion, take order that this ſparke, caſt out at aduenture, and husbanded contrary to his meaning, by the enemies of quietnes, proceed not to a fire of ſedition among his people. And God of his grace, grant him long to Raigne, in all felicity and peace to his glory, and the quiet of the kingdome. Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:9932:30"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
